<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sergeant maior A dialogue of the office of a sergeant maior. VVritten in Spanishe by the Maister of the Campe Francisco de Valdes. And translated into Englishe, by Iohn Thorius.</title>
            <title>Espejo, y deceplina militar. English</title>
            <author>Valdés, Francisco de, militar.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14255</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854207</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19616</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14255)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19616)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 471:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sergeant maior A dialogue of the office of a sergeant maior. VVritten in Spanishe by the Maister of the Campe Francisco de Valdes. And translated into Englishe, by Iohn Thorius.</title>
                  <title>Espejo, y deceplina militar. English</title>
                  <author>Valdés, Francisco de, militar.</author>
                  <author>Thorie, John, b. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Espejo, y deceplina militar.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The office of the sergeant maior.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:1"/>
            <p>The Sergeant Maior.</p>
            <p>A DIALOGVE of the Office of a <hi>Sergeant Maior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten in Spaniſhe by the Maiſter <hi>of the Campe</hi> Franciſco de Valdes. <hi>And tranſlated into Engliſhe,</hi> by Iohn Thorius.</p>
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by John Wolfe.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Knight, Sir Iohn Norris, Lorde Preſident of Munſter. &amp;c.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Iohn Thorius wiſheth increaſe of all <hi>Heroicall verſues.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable: Plutarch hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a tretiſe intituled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In which he ſheweth how men may reap profite by their enemies. And foraſmuch as thys booke was written to inſtruct thoſe that are profeſſed enemyes to our eſtate, I thought that we might reap ſome profite by them, if this theyr Sergeant Maior were as well knowen vnto our men as vnto them ſelues: and that, notſomuch for any poynts of pollicy which might be in their ſouldiers more then in ours, or for that I think them to haue more knowledge in matters concerninge warfare then our Engliſh warriers, who are no whit infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to any of them; as for that theyr orders being kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto vs, wee may the better and more eaſely hurte them and benefit our ſelues by reaſon of this aduantage. I haue therefore beſtowed ſome pains in vnarming this Spanyſh Sergeant and doffing his Caſtilian and hoſtile armour, and haue clothed him in Engliſh apparel, to the end that our men may vſe him to theyr pleaſure, and he finding him ſelfe metamorphoſed, learne how to ſerue Engliſh men. Beſeeching and deſiring your Honor, that as in the fielde you wiſh to be the firſt to encounter, not with the ſtouteſt Sergeant onely, but alſo with the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt Duke, Prince, or King, that profeſſeth enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:19616:3"/> yourſelfe, your Prince, or your Countrey. So you wil at home vouchſafe to protect this SERGEANT MAIOR, who hauing now forſaken his owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, matcheth not in the fielde in Spaniſhe colours, but walketh in London ſtreetes in Engliſhe attyre. And I for my part ſhall thinke my ſelfe much bounden vnto your Honor, if you ſhall accept thys my labour as a ſigne of my good minde. Thus I leaue your Honor to your martiall meditations, beſeeching God, that as our enemyes haue felte your valour, the lowe Countreys inioyed it, and England with an vniuerſall voyce gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally commended it, ſo it may pleaſe his deuine Maieſty to increaſe it, to the glory of his owne Honor, to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of your enemyes, and to the benefite of our Prince and Countrey.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:3"/>
            <head>A Militarie Dialogue of the <hi>Office of the Seargeant Maior.</hi> INTER LOCVTORS.</head>
            <stage>Londonno. Vargas.</stage>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue had better lucke then my ſelfe could wiſh (Maſter <hi>Londonno</hi>) ſéeing that at this time you cannot iuſtly bee excuſed from telling mée that which I haue ſo often requeſted you, and which beſides (if I be well remembred) you haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. But your many affaires (as I take it) haue hetherto hindered, that I haue not obtained my deſire, and your ſelfe as yet not ſatiſfied my requeſt. But now ſéeing my good fortune was ſuch, that we ſhould méete together by our ſelues onely, ſeparated from all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, among the riuers of this moſt pleaſant <hi>Rhene,</hi> I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely beſéeth you, that it be not troubleſome to you, to declare that vnto me, which I ſo gréedily wiſh to knowe: ſéeing that not onely the lawe of friendſhippe doeth binde you thereto, but alſo Chriſtian charitie inioyneth, that the talent receiued from heauen ſhall not be buried, but rather multiplied, that all ſuch may bee taught and inſtructed, as by reaſon of their ignorance, want the light of knowledge.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Certes, good Sir, I conceiued great pleaſure in fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you in ſo pleaſant a place by your ſelfe, accompanied onelie with your manifolde vertues, which neuer ſuffer you to be alone: and I take not this your moſt vertuous curioſitie to bee the leaſt of them, in that (now that your fortune hath brought you to this Militarie profeſſion) you be ſo diligent in learning all ſuch things as a good and valiant ſouldier ought to know. And I woulde to God that I were ſo ſufficient, that I might be able to ſatiſfie this
<pb facs="tcp:19616:4"/> your moſt honeſt deſire. But as much as I can, and as farre as my ſmall wit can reach vnto, I will not refuſe to ſtand you in ſted: And if vntill this time I haue not yet done in this particular, as you ſo greatly haue requeſted me, perſuade your ſelfe, that (as you haue verie well ſayd) my ouer many buſineſſes, and certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the minde withall, (which neuer forſake vs that trauaile as ſtrangers in this waie of humane miſerie) haue cauſed the ſame. But now foraſmuch as we haue ſome leaſure, and the pleaſantnes, ioyntly with the ſolitarines of this place, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your companie (which were inough to amend anie vicous man) inticeth and allureth vs to all vertuous conuerſation. Aſke what you will, for I am readie to obey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I looked for no leſſe curteous anſwere to procéed from your diſcretion and vertues. And I am fully perſwaded, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie one in this our age can fully ſatiſfie my minde concerning this point, you are the man, for the excellent iudgement, continuall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and great experience of many yeres, which I know to be in you, doe aſſure me of it. You alreadie knowe that many dayes ſince, I haue greatly deſired to heare you diſcourſe of the offices of Captaines, Enſignes, Seargeants, and Corporals, what prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minences they haue, and what and how manifolde their duetie is, vnto which euerie one is bound according to the Office which hee doth heare. And I do thinke that you in like manner remember, that I haue requeſted you at ſometimes of leaſure to talke with me concerning the Office of the Seargeant Maior, of which if it would pleaſe you now to intreate, I ſhould thinke my ſelfe behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto you, and we will leaue the firſt particulars to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, ſeeing that (as I haue heard men of greate iudgement, and ſuch as could diſcourſe of matters concerning this profeſſion, ſaie) they which are perfectly acquainted with this charge and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, can eaſily learne all ſuch things as are required in the foreſayd offices and other beſides, whereof I haue not made mention. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that I cannot inough meruaile what the cauſe ſhould be, why many Captaines generall doe often times make choice of perſons, that not only want diſcretion, but are alſo welnigh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wit and experience to beare this office, it being of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and which requireth ſo much abilitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>You haue great reaſon ſurely. For in ſuch like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections many abuſes haue béene and are dayly ſéene, and (I meane
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19616:4"/> not here to preiudice any particular man, but to tell in truth what what I haue ſeene) I ſay the number of them is but ſmall which I haue knowne to be fit and ſufficeint Sergeants Maior. And hence doth it come that many errours haue and daily are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thoſe that exerciſe this office, ſeeing that it hath beene and ordinarily is ſeene, that in time and place of neceſſity, the ſquadron cannot be fourmed, by reaſon of the fault and inhabilitie of the Sergeants Maior. And the ſame which I ſpeake of the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience (which is the chiefeſt) might I alſo ſay of ſome others of unportance, and which are dayly committed in armies, as well in appointing and diſpoſing the watch and Sentinels in the camp, as in many other particulars, which you ſhall more manifeſtly perceiue heareafter in the diſcourſe following. Which leaſt the time eſcape vs in preambles, I inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinently begin, &amp; ſay, that wher as this name of Sergeant hath it originall beginning from the French tong (in which it betokeneth and ſignyfieth as much as in the Latyn tong, miniſter, one that hath the charge or office to doo a thing, a miniſter or ſergeant that miuiſtreth &amp;c. The French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men firſt applyee it to the vſe and cuſtomes of their chaunceries, courts, and iudgement ſeales, vſing certaine miniſters or vnder officers, caling them ſergeants, which ſtoode them in ſteede to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame, declare and execute their ſtatutes, will and ordinaunces, appertayning to law: and afterwards taking it hence, I meane, out of theſe gouned and ciuill exerciſes, they alſo applyed it to the military vſe of armes, and in each company of men, they placed and appointed an officer, calling him a ſergeant, imitating the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome vſed in Courts, and Tribunall ſeates, to the end that the Captains by meanes of ſuch a miniſter or officer, might kéepe due order in placing of theyr men, both marching, lodging and figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And thus much as touching the impoſing of the name which in England, Fraunce and Spayn is receyued in all our warfarre as a naturall word. And the Sergeant Maior is ſo called, becauſe in euery regiment (which is as much as a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane legion) there is a ſergeant who is ſuperintendent and heade ouer all the other Sergeants that are in his regiment: and as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sergeant in ech company taketh the manner of gouernment or order of his Captaine or his lieftenant, ſo the Sergeant Maior receaueth it of the Captaine Generall, or Coronell, or maiſter of the camp, and afterwards from him it paſſeth to the other Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
<pb facs="tcp:19616:5"/> of the ſame regiment, from hand to hand according to the cuſtome. In ſo much that the Sergeant Maior is an officer or generall miniſter of one whole regiment ſuperintendent, and chief of all the Sergeants of the ſame regiment, by the means of whoſe induſtry and helpe, the Captayn, General, or Coronell may giue conuenient order for due gouernment in ordering his men both in marching, lodging and fighting, and other more things alſo vnto this appertayning, theſe thrée things in which the Sergeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior is imployed, are ſuch, that if <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey be wel executed. Wiſhed victory and glory is with great reaſon hoped for. Whereas if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily they be not well executed, much harme enſueth thereby, and the field is loſt and there with goods, life, honour and al. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no inſufficient perſons, but ſuch as are able to diſcharge ſo great an office, and of ſo much waight, ought to be elected and choſen to be Sergeants Maior, and not vnfit men: as ſome thing before we complayned of the careleſnes of ſome Generalls of our times in ſuch like elections.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>What qualityes be thoſe by which thoſe may bée knowne, that are apt and fit, and thoſe alſo that are vnapte and not ſufficient?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Yt is manifeſt and knowen vnto all men that martiall election comprehendeth two ſortes of men, ſome to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and gouerne, and others to obay and to be ruled: and of this latter ſorte are the common ſouldiers, called <hi>Gregarii,</hi> in which both the Gréekes &amp; the Romans required four qualityes. Viz. that they ſhould be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and hardy, that they ſhould be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in armes and warlike exerciſes: that they ſhould be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and that they ſhould be good ſwimmers. And in thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that beare rule and gouerne as Generall, Coronell, Maiſter of the campe, the Sergeant Maior, and the captayns they alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred foure qualyties, and theſe be they. That they ſhould bee very. skilfull in the arte of warre and military ſcience, that they ſhould be vertuous, that they ſhould be men of authority, and that they ſhould be very fortunate. Theſe foure qualityes were vſed by the Greekes and Romanes as an infallible rule, (as in truth it is) to know the ſufficiency or inſufficiency of officers in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. In ſo much that he is ſufficient that it is indowed with the foreſayd foure qualities, and he in whom they be not, is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent. The Sergeant Maior being one of the pryncipall officers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19616:5"/> in warre, ought to haue the foreſayd qualityes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas,</speaker>
               <p>To tell you the truth I doe not well vnderſtand what you meane by thoſe foure qualityes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Loudonno.</speaker>
               <p>I will declare them vnto you in few wordes. Warfare beyng ſo noble a matter as it is, ought to haue it rule and precepts: whence commeth the arte of warre. And as no man is allowed or ſuffered publikely to practiſe phyſicke, or to profeſſe diuinity or any other ſcyence, vnleſſe he haue ſtudyed the ſayd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultyes and be well ſeene in them, ſo were it not good that any one ſhould gouerne and beare office in warfarre, that were not well ſéene in the arte of warre. Which arte ſtandeth a man in ſtéede of a loyall counſayler, of light, in the myddeſt of darkneſſe, and of a guyde in a difficult and doubtfull waye, eſpecyally if hee haue the generall grounds of prudence and chiefe principles of the libeall ſciences.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>For as much as the greater parte of ſouldyers loſe theyr time in games, loue idlenes, and haue not from theyr youth eyther will or power to apply themſelues to any vertuous exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, wanting the due grounds of ſpeculation, they diſpayr that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſhall be able to ſtudy any ſuch arte, and ſo to couer theyr exceeding fault, they ſcoffe at the arte of war, which men attayne vnto by ſtudy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>There is no reaſon why we ſhould aunſwere them that are voyde of all reaſon, and of the infinite reaſons that may be alledged to confound theyr dull ignorance, this onely ſhall ſuffyce at this time that all artes haue both ſpeculation and action or practiſe, and ſo hath warfarre alſo: And they that with a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant courage followe armes and prudently vſe them in war, in tyme attayne to practiſe: but he that ioyntly with this mingleth ſpeculatyon, ſhall attayn both to ſpeculation and practiſe, which are two, and therefore is the ſpeculatiue arte the better and nobler of the two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I now vnderſtand the firſt qualitie, but knowe not yet what you meane by the ſecond, of being vertuous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>This vertue which is required in Militarie offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers is (as <hi>Tullie</hi> declareth it) toylſome labour in affaires, induſtry in doing them, ſpeedineſſe in diſpatching them, conſtance and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the minde in dangers, not ſuffering theyr vnruly affections to beare rule ouer them and ouercome them. The other two qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
<pb facs="tcp:19616:6"/> which are Authoritie and Fortune, doe neceſſarily followe the two former, as the ſhadow followeth the bodie: for, the vertue whereof I ſpake, doth put the Militarie precepts in practiſe, and bringeth them to effect, making a diſpoſition or qualitie of them in the Souldier, whence neceſſarily proceedeth the fame and glory of his valour and deedes, which increaſeth his credit, and bringeth him in authoritie. As for felicitie and good ſucceſſe that ſpringeth from all three, ſkil, vertue and authoritie, for he that by knowledge and experience knoweth what he ought to doe, and is endued with vertue to attempt anie thing, and put it in execution with aduice and authoritie, to the end his Souldiers may beleeue him and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe him, this man ſhall obtaine good ſucceſſe, which is to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate and happie. Therefore the Greekes and Romanes did with good cauſe require, that theſe foreſayd qualities ſhould bee in all and euerie Officer and chiefe Captain of warre, and I for this cauſe will alſo haue them to be in the Seargeant Maior, and yet one more beſides, with which there will be fiue in all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Yet another ſaie you, which I pray you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>That he be ſome thing cunning in Arithmetike: for that ſcience is verie neceſſarie for the forming and making of the Squadrons, which cannot bee made without the ſcience of numbering.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>You demand and require ſo many things in a Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior, that I doubt none ſuch are to be found anſwerable to your deſcription.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Yes marie Sir be there, though they be but few, and there would be many more to be found, if it were not for the fauours, ſutes, and bribes, which as in other things, ſo in the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a Seargeant Maior, diſturbe and impeach the right courſe of election. Furthermore, whereas I am to forme a Seargeant Maior, it is not for our purpoſe to ſéeke out and inquire what kind of men our Scargeantes Maior be, but rather to ſhew and declare what men they and all others ſhould be, and how they ought to be qualified We muſt follow that which is perfeſt, for that which is not perfect may be found at euerie place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>You haue ſhewed mee the ſpring, beginning and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the name of Seargeant Maior and Seargeant, and what the Seargeant Maior is, and the qualities in him required: Now I deſire to know of you what Office the ſame of the Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19616:6"/> Maior is, and in what manner he ought to execute it. But firſt I beſeech you to reſolue me of one doubt, which is, that I knowe not whether they that liued in ancient times paſt, had this Office of the Seargeant Maior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I haue not read that the Lacedemonians, Gréeks and Romanes (among which Nations did warfare flouriſh moſt) haue had it: but we may reade that they had and vſed diuers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Battailes and Squadrons, and I beleeue this to bee the cauſe (if I be not deceiued) that they had no Seargeant Maior, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Office was diſcharged by certaine other Officers, as we may gather out of thoſe that haue written <hi>De <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Militari,</hi> viz. that the Captaine Generall and chiefe head of the Armies, vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and perceiuing of howe greate moment and importance the good order and perfection of the Squadron or Battaile is, in which conſiſteth all the force of the whole Armie, they would truſt no particular man with this Office, but themſelues diſpoſed theyr Armies, and made the Squadrons, of which they vſed ſundrie and different kindes and manners, according to the diuerſitie of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons with which in thoſe times they accuſtomed to encounter with theyr enemies, and alſo their ſouldiers were ſo well inſtructed and ſo ſkilfull, that in a verie great and huge Armie there was not one ſouldier but knew his place in the Squadron: for the eaſier obtaining of which knowledge, there were many Schooles in <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Titus Liuie</hi> writeth, where thoſe yong ſouldiers which they called <hi>Tyrones,</hi> among vs, freſh water ſouldiers, were not onely taught and ſhewed howe to bee apt and quicke in vſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie kinde of weapon, but they were alſo inſtructed howe they ſhould keepe theyr place, that euerie man might haue and knowe his owne ſeuerall place, in which thing they were ſo well inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that it was a verie eaſie matter, and little or no labour, trouble or difficultie at all, to frame and make the Squadrons, and they became dayly the more fit and apt as long as they were not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an hnge &amp; perpetual Armie. And the ſame <hi>Liuie</hi> ſaith, that the young ſouldiers exerciſed themſelues twice a daie, and the old bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſouldiers but once a daie. And this moſt excellent order which the Romanes obſerued aboue all other Nations, cauſed them ſo to enlarge theyr Empyre, and to become almoſt inuincible through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the worlde: whereas notwithſtanding (as <hi>Vegetius</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well ſaith) they were neither ſo great as the Germanes, nor
<pb facs="tcp:19616:7"/> more in number then the French men, nor ſo ſubtill as the Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans, nor ſo many or of ſuch force as the Spaniards, nor ſo wiſe as Gréekes, but the Souldiers exerciſed and inſtructed in Warfare, did conquer and ouercome all theſe difficulties. It were a very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie matter in proofe of this truth, here to alleadge many examples both olde and new of many excellent Captaines, who with lyttle Armies well inſtructed and ſet in good order, haue obtayned victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of innumerable armies and bandes of men naughtily ranked and confuſed. But I will onely rehearſe ſome of them, ſéeing it is not ſtrange to the matter of which we now intreate, neither wyll it be out of the purpoſe to make a ſhort digreſſion to proue this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. And let the firſt example be taken from the great King <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> when he ſet vpon all <hi>Aſia,</hi> and the innumerable bandes of <hi>Darius,</hi> yet with a verie ſmall armie, but wonderfull well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed. <hi>Lucullus</hi> a famous Captaine did get a moſt happie vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie ouer all the greate powers of <hi>Tigranes</hi> with ſo ſmall a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of good Souldiers well trained and ſet in good araie, that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granes</hi> ſeeing them comming towarde his forces, making little account of them, and to mocke with them ſayde, that if they come as Embaſſadours, they were inowe of them, but if to fight, they were verie few. <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> being Proconſull, ſubdued vnto the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> many and rude barbarous Nations, euen from the riuer <hi>Rhene</hi> and ſea Ocean, vntill the ſea Mediterranean. And I praie what made him ſo victorious, but the good order and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline he vſed? And in our daies <hi>Hernando Cortes,</hi> (moſt worthy to be placed among the nine celebrated Captains,) with leſſe then a thouſand and foure ſcore horſe, tooke the great king <hi>Montecuma</hi> within his owne Citie. And at the length onely by the good order he vſed, he did ſubdue the whole kingdome of <hi>Mexico.</hi> And <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando Aluarez</hi> Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> onely with one thouſand of ſmall ſhot, and fiue hundreth Muſkets in <hi>Frisland,</hi> ouerthrew an armie of twelue thouſand men, with which <hi>Lodowicke</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> had entered in that Prouince. To conclude, as touching this point, I ſaie, that ſeeing a Squadron is a companie of ſouldiers placed in order, in which euerie man hath his place appointed him, in ſuch order that-he may fight without hindering others, or being hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his fellowes, and in which all their forces may bee ſo vnited and ioyned together, that they may obtaine theyr-principall intent and end (which is, to become inuincible, and for which end the firſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19616:7"/> warriers that were, did inuent ſo many kindes and manners of Squadrons) we muſt néeds beléeue that that Armie which is beſt ordered, though it be leaſt in number of men, ſhall alwaies (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reaſon) become victorious.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>You haue reſolued me of the thing whereof I doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and now I expect what you will ſaie of that which euen nowe I aſked of you touching the office of the Sergeat Maior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Out of the definition which I before ſet downe, may be gathered, that the Office of the Seargeant Maior conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in three things, viz. in the ſafe order of marching, in the good manner of lodging, and in pitching the field to buckle with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. All other matters that the Sergeants Maior hath to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, muſt of neceſſitie be reduced vnto theſe thrée things onely. For Warfare (as they ſaie who haue written of this ſubiect) hath thrée parts: the one being the preparation for Warre, vnto which part appertayneth the leuying and preſſing, or taking vp of Souldiers, the arming of them, the paying of them, and victualling of them: for all which there are particular Officers appointed, the Searge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Maior hauing nothing to doe therewith. The ſecond parte of Warfare concerneth the Hoaſt: vnto which part appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the marching of the camp, and the lodging of the ſame, and ſo out of this ſecond part of warfare, two of the thrée points in which the Office of the Sergeant Maior conſiſteth do proceed. The third parte of Warfare is, concerning the fighting and ioyning in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle with the enemie, whether it be by ſea or by land, whether in plaine ground or hillie, whether beſieging or béeing beſieged: out of which part of Warfare proceedeth the third parte of the Office of the Seargeant Maior, which conſiſteth principally in ranking his ſouldiers orderly and ſtrongly, when hee formeth and maketh his Squadrons: from which Squadrons as from the chiefe part, I will begin to ſhew you how the Seargeant Maior exerciſeth his Office: and afterwards I will in order procéed ſucceſſiuely to ſhew the ſame in the other two parts of his Office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>It is not long ſince you tolde me what a Squadron is, and therefore now I praie you beginne to make the Squadron, and ſet the Battaile: for this is it wée intend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>The Squadrons are made of a great number of Souldiers, more or leſſe, according to the bigneſſe of the Armie or Hoaſt. And it is neceſſarie that he who taketh his charge in hand,
<pb facs="tcp:19616:8"/> knowe what people euerie companie that is in Regiment hath, how many pike men, and how many harquebuſiers, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time of néede, he continually haue in his head and memory a plat and forme, thereby to ſet a Battle when occaſion is offered, in conceit alwayes forming ſuch Squadrons, as for the preſent time are moſt vſed. As thoſe that are ſquare of grounde, ſquare of number of people, broade in the front, and thoſe that are drawen out in length Hearſe-wiſe. This ought he not onely to doe of the number of thoſe men that are in the Bands or Companies of his Regiment, but of all numbers. For oftentimes it commeth to paſſe that the Seargeants Maior are willed by the Captaines ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to ſet a Battaile of thrée or foure Regiments together, and then if they bee not exerciſed, they ſhall bee ſo vnreadie, and fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many abſurdities, and ſhame themſelues in preſence of theyr Princes, and in the generall iudgement of the whole Hoaſt, and for this cauſe did a friend of ours ſaie verie well, that a Seargeant Maior could not commit a ſmall fault, ſéeing that the Iudges and arbiters thereof were ſo many.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Before you aduantage your diſcourſe, I pray you ſir dayn to tel, me whether there be any more kindes of battayles or ſquadrons then thoſe foure which you haue before named.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Yes mary be there many others, wherof ſome be in vſe among the Italians and Switzers, as thoſe that are horned like a halfe moon, and thoſe alſo that are made like a croſſe, which are approued and thought to be good by many excellente wits, there be alſo other manner of battayls, as thoſe that are made wedgewiſe in forme of a wedge, and thoſe that are made in forme of an egge, and thoſe alſo that are made tryangular wiſe, with many others beſides which are now quite out of vſe, yet I thinke it not amiſſe, nay rather I would iudge it very neceſſary, that the Sergeant Maior ſhould be acquainted with them all, and be exerciſed in ſetting all kindes of battails: ſeeing that occaſſon and place might be offered, where they might be needefull, and it is not good that a man ſhould be ignorant of any thing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng his office, which might chaunce to be neceſſary to aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage himſelfe thereby. But of all battayls thoſe foure which I ſette downe firſt, are moſte in vſe now a dayes, in thoſe places where warfarre flouriſheth moſt, and they bee taken to be the ſtrongeſt battayls, and moſt neceſſary, conſidering the weapons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19616:8"/> that are vſed in this our age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>And which thinke you to be the ſtrongeſt of theſe foure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>They be all of like force and ſtrong inough ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as occaſion and place requireth, for in ſome places the ſquare battayls of ground, or of number of people is beſt, for wee ſhould not doe well to make a ſquare battayle, drawne out in length herſwiſe in ſome places, as in Barbery or ſome other place where the enemy hath a great troupe of horſemen to ſet vpon vs, &amp; we none, but in ſuch a caſe we ought to vſe the ſquare battayle of ground or of number of people, that it beyng ſet vpon by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, they may finde equall reſiſtance at all the foure ſides of the battayle: in other places it were moſte conuenient to vſe thoſe battailes that haue a large front, which I would ordinarily vſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our countreymen, if we were to fighte with our enemy, conſidering that in theſe ſquadrons, by how much the more greate the front is, by ſo much the more men fight in the vantgard, and beſides this, this kinde of battaile aboue all other ſquadrons can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without great difficulty be enuironed about by the enemy. The Germans and Switzers doe greatly vſe ſquare battails dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen out in length, taking that ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be of wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful ſtrength that hath a great courtain: but I would commonly vſe the ſquare battayl of ground, vnleſſe the ſituation of the place compelled mee to doe otherwiſe, iudging this battayl to be moſt proportionable, and of equall force in the vantguard and rereward, and it taketh vp leſſe roome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me I pray you, what order might be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to forme theſe ſquadrons with facillity and quickneſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>To make a ſquare battayl of number of people it will be ſufficient to take the ſquare roote of that number where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">1600</note> the ſquadron is to bee made, and euery one of the our ſides of <note place="margin">40</note> the ſquadron or battayl, ſhall containe as many ſouldiers as the <note place="margin">2500</note> number of the roote is of, as for example, if you wil make a ſquare <note place="margin">50</note> battayle of one thouſand and ſixe hundreth pikes, the ſquare roote of this number is forty, and of ſo many is euery rancke, and if you make it of two thouſand fiue hundreth pikes, the ſquare roote is fifty, that is fifty to euery ranke, which number being multiplied in it ſelfe, fifty times fifty, it maketh the foreſayd number. We wil call the ſquare roote (according to the Arithmeticians) the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:19616:9"/> number which being multiplied in it ſelfe, endeth in the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity or number which you will make the ſquadron of, as you may perceiue in the two foreſayd examples, for in a thouſand and ſixe hundreth there can be no greater number taken out, then that which is multiplyed in it ſelfe, which is forty, and in two thouſand fiue hundreth, there can be no greater then fifty, as by multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you may learne, multipliyng each one of theſe two numbers in it ſelfe, and preſuppoſing (as I mentioned before) that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior ought to be ready in counting, &amp; skilful in cyphering, I ſhall not need to ſtand vpon it any longer, teaching how a man may counte. As for the ſquare battayl of ground, the famous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themacitian <hi>Tartalla,</hi> ſetteth down a rule, how it may be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made and framed. And this is it, if you take this number <note place="margin">2401</note> forty nine, and multiply it in it ſelfe, it maketh two thouſand four hundreth and one, this number muſt be multiplyed by the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe ſouldiers, of which you will make the ſquadron or bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayl, and that which remaineth of this multiplcation you muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide <note place="margin">1000</note> it by a thouſand, and out of the product you muſt take the ſquare roote, and that ſhalbe the number of the ſouldiers that ought to be in euery rank, and diuiding the ſayd quantity of which the ſquadron is to be made, by this ſquare roote, that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth ſhalbe the number of the ranks. Example, if we would make a ſquare battaile of the ſame number of ſouldiers as we did <note place="margin">1600</note> before, viz. one thouſand and ſixe hundreth, we muſt multiply this number by the two thouſand foure hundreth and one, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained of the multiplication, of the number forty nine, and it wil <note place="margin">1600</note> make three millions eight hundreth one and forty thouſand and ſix <note place="margin">241</note> hundreth, which being deuided by one thouſand, there remaine <note place="margin">49</note> thrée thouſand eight hundreth forty and one, and the ſquare roote <note place="margin">3841600</note> of this number is thrée ſcore and one, and if the ſaide quantity of <note place="margin">1000</note> which the ſquadron is to be made, which is one thouſand and ſixe <note place="margin">3841</note> hundreth be deuided, by this ſquare roote of thrée ſcore and one, <note place="margin">61</note> there remayne twenty and ſixe, and of ſo many ranks ſhall the <note place="margin">1000</note> ſquadron be, and then fourtéene remaine ouer plus, which may be <note place="margin">61</note> placed according as the Sergeant Maior thinketh beſt. Ther is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <note place="margin">26</note> way ſhorter then this, to make this kinde of ſquadron, but <note place="margin">14</note> the ſquadron falleth out nothing ſo perfectly, by reaſon of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people that remaine ouer plus, and this is it: you muſt deuide the number of ſouldiers of which you will make your bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19616:9"/> by one and twenty, and taking the ſquare roote out of the product, ſet that which remaineth ouer plus a ſide, and multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſquare roote by ſeuen, you ſhall haue the number of the ſouldiers that muſt be in euery ranke, and multiplying the ſayde ſquare roote by thrée, that which remaineth of the multiplication ſhalbe the number of the rancks, and this being done, multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">21</note> thoſe that remaine ouer plus by twenty and one, the product <note place="margin">1600</note> maketh the number of the ſouldiers that remaine ouer plus, as <note place="margin">21</note> may bee ſeene by the foreſayd example of one thouſand and ſixe <note place="margin">76</note> hundreth men, which being deuided by one and twenty, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct <note place="margin">4</note> is thréeſcore and ſixtéene, and foure remaine ouer plus, and <note place="margin">8</note> the ſquare roote of this number is eight, which being multiplyed <note place="margin">7</note> by ſeauen, maketh ſixe and fifty, and of ſo many ſouldiers ſhall <note place="margin">56</note> euery rancke be, &amp; if the ſaid roote which is eight be multiplyed by <note place="margin">8</note> thrée, it maketh twenty foure, and ſo many ranks ſhall there be in <note place="margin">3</note> the ſquadron, then multiplying the twelue that remaine by one &amp; <note place="margin">24</note> twenty, they make two hundreth fifty and two, which are they <note place="margin">12</note> that were lefte, and foure which remained ouer plus in the deuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <note place="margin">2</note> ſo that all the ouerplus maketh ſixe and fifty, of which (the <note place="margin">252</note> Sergeant Maior adding thrée rancks) the ſquadron is made of <note place="margin">256</note> ſeauen and twenty ranks, nine and fifty ſouldiers to a ranke, and <note place="margin">27</note> ſeuen only remaine ouer plus, but I like the firſt manner better then this (as I told you before) yet it is good to knowe the one as wel as the other The other two manners of ſquadrons, viz. that which is drawen out in length herſewiſe; and that which hath a large front, are framed and made very eaſely, eſpecially if one know how to make the two former kinds of ſquadrons, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wil onely tel you that eyther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is both, for if of the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke of a ſquare battayl made herſewiſe, you make the front, then will it be a broad ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a large front, euen ſo contrarily if of the front of a broad ſquadron you make the flancke, then is the ſame ſquadron made a long ſquadron drawen out in length herſewiſe. Example, if you make a large ſquare of one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth ſouldiers, each ranks will be of thrée ſcore pikes, and the courtin will bee of twenty pikes, but if of this courtin of twentye pikes you make the front, the flanke wilbe of thrée ſcore pikes, and ſo it wilbe a perfect long battaile herſewiſe, obſeruing due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is, that the front of the one be neuer more then thrée times as much as the courtin of the other, as may be vnderſtood
<pb facs="tcp:19616:10"/> by the example aboue ſayd, for the front being of thrée ſcore ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, the flanke is no more then twenty, all theſe manners and faſhions of ſquadrons before ſpecified, may eaſily be made by the Sergeant Maior, if he be skilfull in the ſcience of Arithmeticke, as I ſaide aboue: for otherwiſe it wilbe very hard and troubleſom for him to doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I haue noted in the examples which you haue ſet downe of ſquadrons and battayls, that the moſt of them were in number euen, whereas notwithſtanding I haue hard many ſay, yea and ſtand vpon it, that ſquadrons and ranks ought to be in number odde, and that in auncient times paſt, it was alwaies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but eſpecially in thoſe nations where warfarre did floriſhe moſte. Wherefore I pray you to ſatiſfie mee concerning this pointe before we goe any further.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Opinions there be many that battayls and ſquadrons ought to be odde in number of ſouldiers, and I going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout diuers times to inquire and ſearch out of what importance it is that the ſquadron ſhould be in number odde or euen, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this can make it more or leſſe ſtrong, and hauing read verye curiouſly the authors both auncient and moderne, that entreate of this arte or ſcience martiall, and hauing alſo noted the manner and number which they obſerued in making their battailes and ſpuadrons, I finde as wel by that which I haue ſaid as by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which I will here ſhewe, that it concerneth not the ſtrentgh or weakeneſſe of the battaile, whither it be made in number euen or odde, for I wil ſhew vnto you that obſeruing the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule to make a ſquadron or battayle, there are certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of which if you will make ſquadrons odde in number, you ſhould finde a wonderfull great imperfection therein, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily there be other numbers, of which a man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make ſquadrons of euen number. Example, If you woulde make a ſquare battaile of number of people of two thouſand and fiue hundreth pikes, the ſquare roote of this number is iuſt fifty, and it would be a gret fault to make it of more or leſſe, ſéeing that (as I haue ſaid) a ſquare battayle of number of people can haue no greater perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then to be made of the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that the ſquare root of it is of, and if you will make one, of thrée thouſand and ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth pikes, the ſquare roote of this number is thrée ſcore, and of ſo many ſouldiers will the front of the Squadron be, and this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19616:10"/> is the perfection of it. And as I haue ſette downe two exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples heereof, ſo coulde I ſet downe many more, and I ſaie the ſame of the Squadron, that is made of an odde number. For if you will forme a Squadron or Battayle ſquare in number of people, of two thouſand ſixe hundreth ſouldiers and one, the number of it will be one and fiftie pikes, for that is the ſquare roote of it: and to make it of a greater or leſſer number, it would bée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe. And if you wil make ſuch a Squadron of one thouſand foure ſcore and nine, the fronts of it will be of thrée and thirtie pikes, for this is the ſquare roote of the Squadron. And if you adde anie thing vnto this number, or diminiſh it, the Squadron wil remaine vnperfect. Inſomuch that by that which I finde vſed, and by mine owne opinion, I gather, that Squadrons or Battailes ought to be made according to the number of people of which they be made, and manner how they be made, and as the place where they bée made permitteth. As for the reaſons which ſome alleadge, that in the odde number there is a middle, and in the euen number there is none, as is ſéene by example, that in thrée, fiue, ſeuen and nine there is a middle, wheras in two, foure, ſixe and eight, there is none, and ſo they ſaie, that the ſame middle which is the vnitie (which vnitie is the beginning of all numbers) ſhould be the foundation and baſis of the Squadron, and therefore they holde opinion that it is the ſtronger. They alleadge furthermore, that Martiall men in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times paſt, did not without myſterie vſe the odde number in theyr Squadrons and Battayles, more then the euen number, all which cannot ſuffice to proue that theyr Battailes were therefore the ſtronger, for as you might haue marked, I haue ſufficiently argued and proued wherein the ſtrength and force of a ſquare bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile doth principally conſiſt. For if this onely that the Squadron is made of the odde number maketh it the ſtronger, it is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that anie Squadron whatſoeuer in number odde, though it be but of a ſmall number of men, yet it ſhall bee of more force and ſtrength then anie other Squadron made of a far greater number of ſouldiers, which is in number euen, which is moſt vnlikely and fals. For who knoweth not that a Squadron in the front, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there be fiftie, ſixtie, or eightie, or one hundreth ſouldiers, is ſtronger, then one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath but fiftie or twentie, ſeuen or thrée &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in euery ranke, and ſo likewiſe doth it followe that thoſe Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons ſhall be ſtrong that haue ſeuen and twentie, three and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:19616:11"/> one and fifty or thrée and ſixty, then thoſe that haue but twelue, ſixtéene, four and twenty, or ſixe and thirty: in ſo much that the number odde or euen, maketh not the ſquadron ſtrong, but due proportion according to the quantity of the people of which it is made, together with the place, and aboue all things the valour of the ſouldiers is the right and true ſtrength of battayls, and for as much as they ſaye, that the auncientes did more vſe the odde number then euen (which they cannot eaſely proue) but though it were ſo; yet it is moſte manifeſt, that they did not ſo becauſe they beléeued that the ſquadron was the ſtronger by reaſon that it was odde in number, but they did it being moued with a certaine deuotion and religion, taking this number odde to be conſecrated to theyr Gods, as <hi>Virgill</hi> ſome where mentioneth. <hi>Numero Deusimpari gaudet,</hi> and ſo they being ſo religious in all their actions (but ſpecially the Romanes) they gaue them ſelues more to the obſeruation of this number odde, in framing and making their ſquadrons and battails, then of the number euen. As, for the ſame reaſon and with greater cauſe wee ought to reuerence this number, for that which was vncertaine and unknowne to the heathens and gentils in this particular, being ignorant of the excellency and diety of this number odde, the light of our faith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth manifeſt and knowne vnto vs, beléeuing as we do, that God is <hi>trinus &amp; vn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> But what maketh this deuotion or religious conceipte, for the ſtrength of the ſquadron? and as for the ſeconds reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ought leſſe to be admitted, for where they ſay that the od number hath a middle, and the euen number hath none, how can this make the ſquadron ſtrong? for it is manifeſt that in this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber fifty, there is no middle, and yet if the battayle be ſquare in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of people, and ſo the ſquadron be made of two thouſand and fiue hundreth pikes (as before was ſaide) it cannot bee more ſtronger or perfect: for it is ſquare euerie way hauing fifty ranks, fifty to a ranke, which is the ſquare roote, and if of the ſame nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber two thouſand and fiue hundreth pikes, you would make a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile of the odde number as of fiue and forty, ſeuen and forty, or nine and forty pikes to a ranke, which are all thrée odde, and haue a middle, the ſquadron would be nothing ſo perfect, for that is not the ſquare root of it. And if chaunce we woulde make at the ſquadron of one and fifty or thrée and fifty, it would not fall out in the foreſaide number of two thouſand and fiue hundreth, and ſo we
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19616:11"/> ſhould finde an imperfection, becauſe the ſquare roote exceedeth. But if it were not for this inconuenience of imperfection, that Sergeant Maior that were curious in making his rankes and ſquadrons of the number oddde, though it be for nothing els but onely to ſatiſfie the generall opinion of the moſt that make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of warfarre, who ſéeme continually to looke that the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons ſhould be made of the number odde, I am perſwaded ſhould not do amiſſe, eſpecially when the companies enter or goe from the watch hill, for then the ranks are but ſmall, and it ſéemeth better that they ſhould then be thrée, fiue, or ſeauen to a rank, then foure, ſixe, or eight, and I thinke the reaſon be, becauſe the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle is diſcerned in ſuch ſmall numbers, which cannot ſo eaſely bée ſeene in greater numbers, and it ought eſpecially to bee done by reaſon of the cuſtome which is ordinarily vſed in making rancks odde: and all that which is by cuſtome and vſe receiued, ſeemeth to be beſt and moſt allowed. Neuertheleſſe this ought not to be ſo greatly reſpected, that (as I mentioned before) when the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the people, and forme or faſhion of the Squadron be ſuch, that it requireth to be made of the number euen, it ſhould in anie caſe bee made of the number odde, for they that ſhould ſo do, ſhould commit a foule errour. For ſo in theſe wars of Flanders, when the Prince of Orange paſſed the <hi>Moſe</hi> with his armie, and entered into Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the two armies marching ſo néere the one by the other, that they euery daie looked that they ſhould buckle together, the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> ordained that the maſters of the Campe and Seargeant Maior of theyr thrée Regiments of Spaniſh foot-bands, with the other perſonages that were of his counſell in warre ſhoulde make an aſſemblie: and that the number of the pikes they had in theyr Enſignes being knowen, they ſhould each of them giue theyr voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces concerning the faſhion and forme of which the Squadron ſhould be made. Which was ſo done, and they founde that there were no more pikes in all the thrée Regiments then one thouſand and two hundreth, and they all agréed that they ſhoulde make a broade Battayle with a large front. Which Squadron conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the number of the piks, and obſeruing proportion, could haue no more then thrée ſcore ſouldiers in the front of it, and twentie in the courtin, which iuſtly make vp the full number of one thouſand and two hundreth: and ſo it was done. and becauſe they marching through ſome ſtraight and narowe grounds, the Squadron coulde
<pb facs="tcp:19616:12"/> not march with ſo many in the front, it was diuided into three partes, in ſuch manner, that the Regiment of <hi>Naples,</hi> which had ſixe hundred pikes ſhould march with thirtie pikes in the front, and the Regiment of <hi>Lombardie</hi> which had thrée hundreth and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie pikes, ſhould march with ſixtéene pikes in each ranke, and the Regiment of <hi>Sicil</hi> which had two hundreth and foure ſcore pikes ſhould haue fouretéene in the front. And now you may ſee, that all theſe thrée Battailes were of the number euen, and being ioyned all thrée in one, they made a large fronted Squadron of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber euen. For the quantitie of pikes which were in each regiment and the forme of the Battayle did ſo require it. And it is to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeued, that if there had bene anie imperfection in theſe Squadrons and Battayles, ſo great a Captaine of Warre, and ſo worthie a, ſouldier as the Duke was, would not haue permitted it to be done in ſuch order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I remaine ſatiſfied as touching this particular, and in truth before your diſcourſe, I was fully perſuaded that all ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſhould neceſſarily be made of the number odde. But now I doubt not of it: and therefore I praie you continue on your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and tell me what you thinke of certaine rules ſet downe by one <hi>Cataneus Nouares,</hi> and of ſome others, which (if I bee well remembred) I haue ſeene, thereby to forme all kindes and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Battailes, doe you account them neceſſarie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>They helpe much, but thoſe men chiefly that can not cypher, but I would not haue anie one bound vnto them one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For ſo, if a man ſhould take them out of their <hi>A B C</hi> booke (as men ſaie) they would incontinently be vnoone. I ſaie, if occaſion were offred them to make a ſquadron or battaile of a number, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from the number which they finde ſet downe, they ſhoulde verie quickly ſpie theyr vnreadineſſe, and acknowlege their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. And heereupon I rehearſe the ſame which I haue ſpoken before, that nothing is better for the Seargeant Maior to ſhunne weariſomneſſe and difficultie in making and framing all kindes of Battailes and Squadrons, then dexteritie &amp; readines in counting, ioyntly with a continuall habite or diſpoſition of forming and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming diverſe kinds of ſquadrens in his head, by the helpe of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie. And this ought he likewiſe to put in practiſe before neceſſity conſtraineth him to doe it. And ſo hee may when his Regiment marcheth either to the lodging or from the lodging, exerciſe his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19616:12"/> people, and by experience &amp; practiſe ſée that which he is taught by theorie and contemplation. And foraſmuch as in that which you aſked of me firſt, of the manner how to make Squadrons with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie and ſpeed, is not onely contained and comprehended to giue rules how to forme them ſpéedily and readily, but alſo to ſhew how that confuſion may be ſhunned which often is cauſed (but eſpecially among the Spaniards) by thoſe that contend and ſtriue to bee pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the firſt ranke of the vauntgard, inſomuch that it falleth out verie often, that much time paſſeth before the Seargeant Maior with all the Captaines together, can make vp the Squadron. I ſaie, that ſéeing the chiefe care and charge to auoide this inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, concerneth the Seargeant Maior. Hee ought to take ſuch order with the Enſignes and companies before they come to this point, that the ſayde confuſion and diſobedience may bee excuſed. And it ſhal be auoyded if ſuch order be taken, that all the Enſignes knowe before, that the firſt rankes ſhall bee made of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie or Companies that be of the watch that daie, and they ſhall be ſeconded by them that were of the watch before, and next to them ſhal they follow that firſt come to the ſquadron, continually aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing the Officers, not to ſuffer anie Souldiers of their Enſignes or Companies come, anie peece of their armour wanting. For in this caſe, though it be theyr turne to fight in the vauntgarde, yet they ſhall be turned to the rereward, and looſe theyr precheminence becauſe they come not well and orderly armed, and others may be iuſtly placed in theyr roomes: and becauſe ſometimes arme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called, and the companies running altogether to the place of armes, this order cannot be obſerued, ſéeing that in time of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, aboue al things this muſt be attended, that the Squadron may be formed with all celeritie and quickneſſe. It is conuenient that the Seargeant Maior, (if ſo be the foreſaid inconuenience hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen) diſpoſe the confuſed &amp; diſorded multitude of people, ſetting the Captaines before, and then take the Squadron out of the flanke or rereward, if he thinke it moſt commodious. Which he may doe with great facilitie: for ſo he leaueth them which were the cauſe of that confuſion deceyed of their intent, and ſo hee ſhall performe two things, the one is, that he ſpéedilie doth make vp his ſquadron, the other that he correcteth and puniſheth the diſobedient with this diſgrace, leauing them all in the rereward, and thence forward ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Sergeant Maior vſeth riddance and diſpatch. Leauing
<pb facs="tcp:19616:13"/> them with the mocke, they will be glad to obey, and preſently get in order. I haue my ſelfe vſed this remedie, and euerie time that I ſo did, I had done, and almoſt wholy made the Squadron of my Regiment, before the Sergeant Maior could in other Regiments frame the formoſt rankes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I was verie glad to vnderſtande how this confuſion may be expelled, which is ſo vſuall in the making and framing of ſquadrons, and moſt of all among the Spaniardes, for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beléeue that in anie other nation men bee ſo diſobedient, and make ſuch a doe to be placed in the firſt ranke, but that euerie one doth obey and content himſelfe with the place which is appointed him, or by lot falleth vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>So they ought to doe all of them, for vnto him that will fight valiantly and doe his dutie, occaſion will neuer bée failing to ſhew his good minde in Warre, and knowe ſurely that many that make ſo much a doe to provide a place for themſelues in the firſt ranke of the Squadron, the deſire they haue to fight, doth not drawe them vnto it, but they bée onely vaine ſhewes, by which they pretend to recouer credit, and gaine the name and title of valiantneſſe, though wée cannot denie neuertheleſſe but that ſome are moued to procure them that place by theyr valour and good zeale, Yet cannot a good and valyant Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier in anie thing ſo néere hit the marke, as in obeying: and this is the principall vertue which a ſouldier ought to haue ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes as an obiecte at the daie that hée taketh the Pike in Warres. If this bée wanting in him, hee hath none of anie value or eſtimation: for obedience is the grounde, baſis, and foundation of all good diſcipline.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Let vs paſſe on if you pleaſe, for I feare me the time will be ſcant for the number of doubts which I pretend to aſke of you. And tell me now ſéeing you haue made vp the ſquadron with pikes, how they ought to be lined, how many and how bigge the ſléeues ought to be, &amp; how far diſtant from the ſquadron, for in good ſooth, I haue heard diuers opinions concerning this particular.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Truely no man that is a ſouldier is ignorant that the battaile of pikes ought ot be garded about with Gunnes, putting a rowe of Harquebuziers cloſe to the other rowe of Pikes, ſo that there bee as many rowes of Harquebuziers at eache ſide as there bee of Pikes, and to obſerue the true man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19616:13"/> of liuing of the ſquadron, there ought to be no more rows of hargubuzers, then could be garded by the pikes, eſpecially where the enemy hath greteſt ſtore of horſemen, and ſo, ſeeing that ther cannot be aboue fiue hargubuzers vnder the fauor of the pikes, with ſo many rows (to my mynd) ought the ſquadron to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, but in caſe that this inconuenience be not, that the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayl is not like to be ſet vpon with troupes of horſes, then may the Sergeant Maior line the battayle with a greater number of hargubuzers, as hee thinketh beſt according to the quantity of gunne-men hee hath in his enſignes, hauing a regard and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration that hee want no hargubuzers to make the ſléeues, which ought not to be aboue foure, and leſſe, according as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity requireth and the place permitteth. Theſe ought to haue their due proportion, and I would not haue them to bee made of more then thrée hundreth ſhotte, nor of leſſe then two hundreth, and in caſe that many hargubuzers remaine after the battaile is furniſhed and cloſed vp, I would rather make foure ſleeues of the foreſayd number then two of a greater quantity. For ordinarily, when the ſléeues be very great and improportionable, it is a hard matter to rule and gouerne them in good order without confuſion, and two ſléeues of three hundreth ſouldiers a piece, can be ordered and gouerned far better, and eaſier then one ſleeue of ſix hundreth ſouldiers. And he that will try this, ſhall finde it ſo manifeſt and deare by experience, that I will not here labor to proue it to be ſo with more reaſons or argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. The place of theſe ſleeues ought to be at the corners of the ſquadrons, after ſuch order that they be not very far aparted from the ſquadron. For euen as the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men make a croſſe defence to the courtins of a caſtle, ſo the ſleeues vnto the battayl, and they be the ſtronger being vnder the fauor of the pikes: and as a caſtle hath it whole perfection ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one. The courtins, horſemen, and ditches. After the ſame manner is a ſquadron perfit, when the pikes being placed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient order, are lined with gnus, and fortified with the ſléeues of hargubuzers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you ſir, let it not grieue you to ſtay here a while, for I deſire greedily that you ſhould reſolue me of a certayn doubt, which I haue ſeene ſome make vppon this which I nowe ſhall ſay. You well know that ordinarily in the Spaniſh foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, there be many more hargubuzers then pykes, for we ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:19616:14"/> ſee nine thouſand footmen together, among which there be ſcar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e one thouſand and fiue hundreth pikemen, all the reſt being gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in ſo much that the ſquadron being lined, and four ſleeues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made vnto it (&amp; that is the moſt that you ſay it ought to haue) yet ther remayneth a great quantity ouer plus, but I pray you where thinke you that theſe hargubuzers may bee ſet to bee ſafe from the troups of the enemyes horſemen, for it falleth out diuers times that we wage wars in Barbery, where the enemy haue ſo many horſe, and we but few or none, and as in Barbery, ſo might this inconuenience chance in other places.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Very well haue you asked, and I haue diuers times hard this matter diſputed vppon, and I haue more times the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once thought of this, nether is it long ſince I ſpake of it before the Captayn generall, and that which I ſayd there will I here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate. Viz. that I am of opinion, that thoſe hargubuzers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be any where placed in ſafety, but in the middeſt of the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron or battails of pikes, where though we could haue no other fruite or ſeruice of them, then to haue them ſure and kept ſafe ther vntill ſuch time that we ſhould haue neede of them, I thinke that this were very much, and yet do I not knowe why, but that they may greatly fauour the ſquadron and doe it much good, with great dammage to the enemies, if they did but regard when the pikes are couched on that ſide of the ſquadron which is ſet vpon by the ennemyes, that then the pikemen ſhould ſome thing bend theyr bodies <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nclining downewards: for ſo might the hargubuzers that are in the centre of the ſquadron haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity fréely to diſcharge theyr péeces on their ennemy without any hurt or preiudice to the pikemen, and though this ſéeme to be ſomething hard and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto them that haue not vſed it, and put it in practiſe, yet ſo they would exerciſe themſelues in trying and doing it ſometimes, they would finde it to be moſt eaſy. For farre more difficult and troubleſome was that which the Romans did, who making thrée ſquadrons of theyr foot bands, when the firſt was defeated, at the laſt driuen to great extremity, and grieuouſly oppreſſed by the ennemy, it was receiued within the ſecond, without diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring either of them, and euen ſo was both the firſt and ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celued within the third, without confuſion of any of them all, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity vrging them thereto, which no doubt by reaſon of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vſe was eaſy vnto them to doe: for what thing is there ſo hard
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19616:14"/> and difficult, which cannot be made eaſy by vſe and exerciſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Why, but how doe you vnderſtand that the ſhot ſhould be within the pikes? you by hap, meane that one hargubu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer ſhould be ſet betweene two pikes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>No, not ſo, for it is likely tha ſo the order would bee broken and marred, but I intend that withint the midſt of the ſquadron and centre of it there ſhould be a place, wher the hargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buzers ſhold be placed in their order, &amp; may be without any offence or hinderance to the pikes: and ſo the Sergeant Maior ſhould not doe amiſſe to caſt what ſhot he hath, and hauing conſidered how many argubuzers are neceſſary to line the ſquadron and to make the ſleeues, aboue al thing to ſet them that remaine ouerplus in order ſquarewiſe, and compas them about with the pikeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is to be done (as you very well noted aboue) wher the enemy hath great company of horſemen and we lacke them: For it is moſte manifeſt that ſhot only cannot reſiſt the ſtrength of horeſemen: though neuertheleſſe it hath more then once or twiſe bin ſeen that hargubuzers haue bin charged by a troup of horſ, and yet haue not bin defeated: but for all this no man can deny that the valour of the hargubuzers was not ſo much the cauſe of it, as the puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and cowardiſe of the horſemen: for the vttermoſt of theyr powers is to diſcharge their pieces vpon the ſquadron and battayl of the horſemen which ſett vpon them, and being compaſſed and enuironed about by them, hauing no defence by their ſwords, are not able to withſtand the vehement charge of the horſemen, which is onely graunted vnto the pike, and ſo of force, if they want this fauour, they muſt alwayes be ouerthrowne, if the horſemen quit them ſelues accordingly. But in other places where the ſaid incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience is not offered, but the battail is to be fought only againſt foot bands, there ſhot doth great ſeruice, and victory hath very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beene obtayned by hargubuzers onely. But for al this, I am not of opinion that among our Spaniſh nation nor the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, there ſhould be a greater number of hargubuzers then pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the companies: as for the Switzers and Germans, their pikes are much worth, but their gunnes are very lightly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I haue taken great pleaſure in the diſcourſe which you haue made vpon the doubt I moued, &amp; now ſeing you haue made the Squadron and Battayle. Tell me I praie you how the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant
<pb facs="tcp:19616:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Maior ought to behaue himſelfe when hee marcheth with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>This which you now aſke, is not the leaſt care which the Sergeant Maior ought to haue in his office, ſéeing it is a matter of ſo great moment and importaunce, to leade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple marching in good order, which is ſo much the more harde and troubleſome to bée done, by howe much the more you ſée all men generallie abhorre to be tyed to order, and eſpeciallie our Spaniſh foote men, who beeing (by reaſon of the climate more cholerike then of anie other complection) take it ſomething impatientlie to goe in order. For you cannot ſo ſoone ſette them in order, but ſtraight vppon the leaſt occaſion in the worlde, they will bee diſordered again. As when they meet with ſome place by the way that is ſomething narrowe, or when they become wearie and hotte, going to ſeeke water, and ſo ſeparate themſelues from the companies to goe and drinke, yea, and for other cauſes, nothing ſo reaſonable as this: but al this proceedeth partly of the ill diſcipline that is nowe a dayes vſed in Warres: and partly of the fault and careleſneſſe of the Officers. For there is no doubt but that if the Souldier did knowe that if he did goe out of order, he ſhould bée puniſhed ſo ſeuerely as they were puniſhed in auncient times paſt that ſerued among the Romanes, none of them durſt goe a whit out of the waie, or doe otherwiſe then he is commaunded to doe: but becauſe men ſee howe ſlacklie ſuch offences are puniſhed, they doe not regard whether they goe in order or not: but now ſeeing that in this age the diſobedience of Souldiers is not ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſlie puniſhed, as it was in that auncient Martiall diſcipline. If the Officers both vpper and vnder were ſo diligent and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as is required, and as they are bound to bee, theſe inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences might eaſilie bee remedied. For to bring which thing to paſſe, I will ſhew you what order I thinke may be taken. But aboue all other things, I will not paſſe thoſe things with ſilence which the Seargeant Maior ought to doe before hee marcheth with his people, being in the field. I ſaie then that the Searge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Maior ought firſt of all to goe to the Captaine Generall to to take directions, and knowe whether his Regiment bee to marche in the vauntgarde, battayle, or rerewarde, which is ordinarilie done the night before the Armie marcheth (though notwithſtanding ſometimes the Generall will not giue the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19616:15"/> for worthy reſpects, til the very houre that they are to march and hee ought to bee verie well informed of the waie, eſpecially when it is his Regimentes turne to marche in the vauntgarde, though it bée verie neceſſarie at all times to knowe the wayes of the Countrie verie well and perfectlie, through which hee may moſt fitly marche with his people out of the Campe: and by faulte héereof it doeth not verie ſeldome come to paſſe, that many Seargeant Maiors haue béene confounded and ſhamed in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of theyr Generalles, guiding theyr Regimentes by wayes that are ſtopte and cumbered with Cartes, and other baggages of the Campe, ſometimes bringing theyr ſouldiers through ſuch narrowe wayes and ſtraightes, that they cannot paſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they breake theyr order: for at the raiſing and departing of the Campe (as you haue ſeene) the horſe-men doe ſo croſſe vp and downe in all partes, and the Trumpettes and Drummes make ſuch a noiſe, that vnleſſe hée bée verie well foreſéene, and knowe perfectlie the waie which hée is to take, and through which waie he is to bring forth his Companies, commonly hee ſhall fal into theſe inconueniences, principally when the Camp de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth by night, or in ſuch dayes as are cloudie. Wherefore it is neceſſarie that the Seargeant Maior, if it bee poſſible, ſhould bee ſingularly well informed of ths ſcituation of the Countrie, through which he is to paſſe, and of the diſtaunce betweene cue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place, the quantitie of the wayes, with theyr abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, hilles, valleyes, fountaynes, riuers. And to be the more ſure, hee ought to haue skilfull Warfarers and faythfull guides. Then the order being knowen and the waie alſo, and the houre come of departure, hee ought to giue order that the Drum Maior gather the Companyes together, and that the Captaine of the fielde cauſe the baggage to bee loden, and then hee ought ſpeedily to bring his Enſignes from theyr quarters to the place of Armes, and there to forme his Squadron, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the Captaynes, eache one in theyr orders, they ought to marche in that daie, and to diſpoſe the Seargeantes in ſuch manner, that euerie one of them doe knowe what people they muſt gouerne and keepe in order: and becauſe it is verie ſeldome ſeene that the wayes are large inoughe for the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron to marche with the whole front, hee ſhall make his ranke no greater, then that the people may marche commody<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,
<pb facs="tcp:19616:16"/> alwaies hauing conſideration that the ranke be neuer leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer (if the waie ſuffer it) then the thirde parte of the front of this Squadron or Battaile. As for example. If the fronte of this Battaile bée of one and twentie men, ſeauen men ſhall marche in a ranke: and ſo likewiſe of other Battailes. For hee ought alwayes to bee very carefull in procuring his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes to bee lead in ſuche order, that occaſion of neceſſitie bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered, hee may with all ſpéede and celeritie make vp his Squadron. Nowe the Captaines and Officers beeing ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as I haue ſayde, and the Regiment marching, the Searge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Maior his right place is in the vauntgarde of the Regiment, where it moſt commonly concerneth the maiſter of the Campe or Colonnell to go. And I ſaie moſt commonly, becauſe if chance we ſhould leaue the enemie behinde vs. The rereward is a more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place for the Colonnell to march in. And foraſmuch as the Sergeant Maior is his inſtrument, by meanes of whome hee ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the order vnto the Captaynes and Companies. He ought to ſtand néere to his perſon, but he ought in ſuch maner to be there, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he neglect not ſometimes to make a ſtand and ſtaie himſelfe, and ſée the whole Regiment paſſe: and if he finde anie retchleſneſſe or negligence in the Sergeants, not diſcharging their duetie, in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the people committed to theyr gouernment, to goe in good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: he ought to blame and rebuke them ſeuerely, inſomuch that none of the Sergeantes ought to forbeare anie fault or negligence whereby the order may be marred: but diligently to take héede, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order neuer be broken, if it be poſſible. And if it chance to be broken (as it happeneth ſometimes by reaſon of the ſtreightnes of the waies) they ought to be verie carefull in making it vp againe. For which if it be néedful that the vantgard make a ſtand, one of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Officers ſhall incontinently goe to informe the Sergeant Maior of it. And I am of opinion, that no Sergeant, Enſigne or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſhoulde paſſe the worde through the Squadron, ſaying, Stand, or March from hand to hand (as it is many times done ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnaduiſedly) vnleſſe the neceſſitie bée ſuch, that they cannot haue time to ſignifie it vnto the Colonnell or Seargeant Maior. For by reaſon of this abuſe, that euerie Officer, and vppon euerie occaſion that is offered, doth paſſe the worde, many inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces may doe ſpring, and the Officers will take vppon them to doe thoſe things that appertayne vnto the ſuperiours, vſurping that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19616:16"/> preheminence which is onely graunted vnto the Colonnel as head of the Regiment, and vnto the Seargeant Maior, as the generall guide of the Squadron. And now this is become ſo common, that not onely the Officers, but alſo the common ſouldiers, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect or diſcretion, for the leaſt cauſe in the world, do vſe to paſſe the word. Whence it commeth to paſſe, that ſometimes when for matters of importance, the ſuperiour paſſe the worde, it doth not paſſe ſo ſpeedily as it ſhould, by reaſon that it is neglected &amp; naught ſet by, &amp; ſo for the moſt part it remaineth in the middle of the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron ſans paſſing to the vantgard, the ſouldiers thinking &amp; perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues, that it commeth not by commandement of the ſuperiours. But if they were ſure that none had authoritie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it to be paſſed but the ſuperiors, they would incontinently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and doe as they are commanded. And therefore to ſhunne and anoide this inconuenience in a matter ſo important, as to kéep the ſquadron in good order, it is very neceſſarie that this preheminence ſhould be onely reſcrued for the two vpper officers. And it is moſt iuſt that ſuch Officers or ſouldiers that dareth firſt paſſe the word ſhould not remaine vnpuniſhed. I will aduertiſe you howe that it is neceſſarie that the people ſhoulde ſometimes make a ſtande, as wel that the ſouldiers may reſt themſelues a while, and eat of that which they vſe to carrie in theyr ſcrippes or bagges, as alſo that they may the better kéepe themſelues in good order, hauing breathed a little after theyr wearineſſe. And the Seargeant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ought to procure ſuche ſtandes to bee made néere ſome water, where the Souldiers may drinke and refreſhe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the Officers ought to bee verie diligent in looking to the Souldyers, that none of them at ſuch ſtandes get out of the Squadron, and make anie miſrule in the neighbour pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and much leſſe that anie of them enter into Orchardes to endomage the Huſbandmen. For all thoſe things are alienate and eſtraunged from good diſcipline. And if the Souldier ſhould bee permitted to bée licentious in theſe trifles and ſmall things, they woulde not afterwardes bee able to refraine from the ſame in greater matters. Howbeit I cannot count it a ſmall thing that the Souldier ſhoulde leaue his place and diſranke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ranging in the poſſeſſions and groundes of the poore people, and ſo I cannot patiently thinke vppon the greate negligence and in conſideration of certaine Officers, that doe
<pb facs="tcp:19616:17"/> not only not repreſſe ſuch diſorders among the ſouldiers, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alſo oftentimes are the firſt that ſhewe them the waie and helpe to doe it. Who ought not onely to be depriued of theyr Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as vnworthie to haue them, but alſo to bee puniſhed with greater and more grieuous puniſhment, as tranſgreſſors of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall diſcipline.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>By that which you haue verie well ſpoken, we may eaſily gather that the retchleſneſſe and negligence of Officers is the chiefe cauſe of diſorder: and no doubt, if that care were both in the ſouldiers &amp; officers which is required in them, they ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies march in good order. And I take it to be a matter verie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, that the word ſhould not be paſſed in the ſquadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but with great regard &amp; conſideration, and I ſuppoſe it verie neceſſarie that ſuch ſtands ſhould be made, that the ſouldiers may reſt a litle. In déed the Gunners can better abide the troubleſomnes of the waie without reſting, as men that go looſe, &amp; not paſſed with the heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and waight of armors: but corſiets cannot anie waie hold out, but muſt néeds make ſtaies, eſpecially in daies that are extreamly hot. And I haue often ſéene ſome neglect their offices, &amp; ſtay when they haue bin commanded to march: and many ſouldiers being he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy armed haue bin choked, ſtriuing to do more then they could do, marching in their armor. And certes it is a ſhame for ſome Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants Maior to ſée how vntowardly they leade theyr ſquadrons, and how vnaduiſedly they march, obſeruing no order, onely for not conſidering when it is neceſſarie for them to make ſtands: whence it commeth to paſſe, that they leade a ſquadron orderly, but drawe as it were a long rope after them three or foure miles, oftentimes being betweene the vantgard and the rereward: in ſuch manner, that the enemie with a far leſſer number then thoſe Seargeants Maior haue in their Regiments, might verie eaſily do them much harme, and ſo they march in greate daunger in one houre through their negligence, to looſe al the credit, honor and reputation, which they haue gotten in many yeres. And although the Maiſter of the Camp or Colonnel be the chiefe of the Regiment, and therfore (as vnto ſuch a one) the honor or ſhame of the good or ill ſucceſſe of the companies, appertaineth principally vnto him, yet neuertheles the Seargant Maior hath a good ſhare therein: for as much as I can gather by your diſcourſe, and (if my memorie deceiue me not) euer ſince I haue giuen my ſelfe to this profeſſion, I haue alwaies ſéene
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19616:17"/> that not only the common iudgement of all men, but alſo the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Generals do vſe to praiſe or blame the Seargeantes Maior, becauſe they leade their Regiments in good or ill order, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anie other whatſoeuer, as ſuch officers whom the ordering of the ſquadron chiefly concerneth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lond.</speaker>
               <p>So it is in truth, for all this care &amp; charge doth properly and wholy appertayn vnto the Sergeant Maior, and he ought not to excuſe himſelfe of his negligence or vnability, blaming the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants or officers of his regiment, for they do all of them obay his orders and doe according to his directions, and alſo they he more or leſſe, diligent or ſlow, according to the watchfulnes or ſlowneſſe of the Sergeant Maior who commandeth them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Now I pray you tell me how the people of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment ought to be deuided when it marcheth, who ought to go in the vantguard, who in battayl, and who in rereward, and what place the ſtandards or enſignes ought to haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I haue already told you aboue (if my remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce kéepe touch with me) that the Sergeant Maior ought to procure his people to march in ſuch manner and ſo well ordered, that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of neceſſity enforcing him, he may alwayes with great eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and facillity forme and make his ſquadron. And to attayn vnto this, I thinke this to be the order he ought to obſerue. Firſt in the vantguard marcheth the ſléeue of hargubuzers of the right hand of the ſquadron (which ſléeue as we haue before ſayd, ought to be made before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany be brought forth of the camp) which ordinarily is one company of gun-men, of the two that are in one regiment, next after followeth the lining of the ſame right hand, being of hargubuzers, and after that follow the pikes according to the manner before ſhewed. And becauſe among other things that happen to be done vnaduiſedly in a ſquadron, it is a very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemly thing to ſe the enſigns born ſo out of order &amp; ouerthwartly, ſomtimes at one ſide and ſometimes at another. The Sergeant Maior ought to cauſe them to be placed ſo, that the ſquadron being made, they be alwaies in their proper places, which is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt and centre of the battayl, next enſueth the lining of hargubuzers, of the left hand, and laſt of al in the rereward marcheth the ſleeue of hargubuzers, being one of the two companies of gun-men that are alwaies in one regiment. And thus you ſee that after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the people marcheth being parted and deuided, &amp; yet the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron
<pb facs="tcp:19616:18"/> is incontinently formed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you why ſay you that the ſleeue and lining of the right hand ſhould goe before the ſleeue and lining of the left<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hand? it may be there is ſome miſtery in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I know not of any other miſtery, but this that in all our actions, wee ought to apply our ſelues to perfection as neare as wee poſſibly can, and for as much as the right hand is the nobleſt and moſt perfect, it is better we ſhould beginne thence, then from the lefte hand to forme the ſquadron, and alſo to vndo it or breake it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſeeing that you haue told me how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ought to march, I deſire you to know where the baggage of theſe companies may be carried, that it may both be ſafe, and yet not hinder the people of the regiment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>When an army marcheth, this conſideration ought to be had, that if the enemy be before in the vant guard of the way, the baggage ought to be in the rereward, and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the enemy be behind the army our baggage ſhall be caried in the vantguard, and if the enemies camp be at the right hand of the way, our baggage ſhalbe put at the left hand of our campe, and if the enemy be on the other ſide we ought to follow the ſame order, carrying our baggage at the right hand of our army. And ſo ſhall the battail continually be a wal and defence to our baggage, and if occaſion be offered that the two armies ſhould ioyne in fight, as they march, it cannot hinder them, and beſides this certain troups of horſe do ordinarily go to guard the baggage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſuddayn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions and aſſaults of horſemen ſent out by the enemy, and this very ſame order ought alſo to be obſerued, marching with one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment by it ſelfe only. But in caſe we were far from the enemy, I would haue the baggage for a good conſideration march in the vantguard with a troupe of hargubuzers to guide it, for it is a great commodity for the ſouldiers, when they come to their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters weary with going, to finde their tents planted, and their fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ready without ſtaiyng for it, after they be come to the place where they are to be lodged, comming many times wette and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dead for hunger. And beſides this if any thing ſhould chaunce to fal by the way, the owner may ſaue it, ſéeing it in danger to fal, or be loſt, and ſo euery one may looke vnto his things that nothing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19616:18"/> be loſt, which they could not do, if their baggage were carried in the rereward behinde the battayle.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Certes it is moſt true, that all theſe commodityes be had by carriyng the baggage in the vantguard, whereas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is gotten by carriyng of it in the rereward, but loſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity, for daily wee ſée that ſome one or other playneth that he hath loſt one thing or other, and it chanceth euery day that many things are loſte or taken through the negligence of naughty ſeruants and boies, their maſters not being there to ſée their bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, or to look vnto it, which if it were carried in the vantguard vndoubtedly ſhould not be loſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I wil haue you to vnderſtand, (before we leaue this particular, which we now ſpeake off, that occaſion might be offered, where the baggage could be ſafely carried in neither of the foreſaid places, and then it would be neceſſary that it ſhoulde bee carried in the midſt of the ſquadron after the ſame manner as I ſayd aboue of the ſhotte that remained ouer plus, for if we ſhoulde march with our army in Barbery or any other place, where the enemy hath great ſtore of horſe, and we none, it were neceſſarye that our baggage ſhould be in the midſt and centre of our ſqnadro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if we would not loſe it, for ſéeing that that litle which the ſouldiers haue, is there, it is great reaſon it ſhould be carefully looked vnto, and ſafely garded, and this ought the rather bee procured, for that the reputation is great which we loſe, if the enemy ſpoile vs of it, glorioſly bragging and vanting that they tooke ſome priſe from vs againſt our wills in deſpighte of vs. Whereof among other vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt Captaynes, <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> lefte vs a worthy example, when hee (according to <hi>Suetonius</hi>) being forced by the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency and ciuill ſury of them of Alexandria, to retire, did caſt him ſelfe vnto the Riuer Nilus, and carried in one hande his booke of commentaries holding it on hie, that it might take no wette, and ſwimmed with the other, holding his veſture in his mouth, that his enemy ſhould not glory of any ſpoile of his. But in caſe that without manifeſt daunger that the people bee defeated and ſpoiled this cannot be done, the goods ought to be abandoned, and forſaken to conſerue the principall, which hath not onely ben done by many noble and excellent Captains, but alſo ſome haue of purpoſe lefte their carriage in the enemies power, offering
<pb facs="tcp:19616:19"/> the occaſion in robbing of it, and gathering the ſpoile to diſorder themſelues, to the end that by meanes of this pollicy they might with leſſe trouble and great facillity obtaine the victory of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I had forgotten to aske you where you think that the horſes of the footemen as wel corſlets as Hargubuzers ſhould goe, and like wiſe where the ſeruants and lackeis ſhall cary their maiſters pikes when they ride? for I haue ſeene this vſed diuerſly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>You know that by al good diſcipline it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden that any footeman ſhall goe forth of the lodging, or muche leſſe entre in it on horſe backe: but alwaies in going forth he ought to accompany his band or enſigne, at the leaſt a mile, or an halfe, and euen ſo in comming to the lodging within a mile or halfe a mile of it hee ought to light, ſeeing that their horſes that vſe to ride may eaſily goe at the flanke of the battayle if the wayes be broad inough, and if not, at the tayle, till they may ride. And it ought not to bee ſuffered in any caſe, that the ſouldiers ſhould get vppon their horſes, before their Captaines that marche on foote, take horſe: and then riding and ſetting them ſelues in order by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and officer that leadeth them (who ought before by the Seargeant Maior to bee named and appointed) they ſhall place them ſelues if they bee hargubuzers of the vantguard, ſtraight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the ſame: and if they be pykemen, they ſhall ride behinde their pikes, the ſame ſhall the hargubuzers doe that march in the rerewarde, placing them ſelues in the taile of the ſquadron, and the ſeruaunts of ſuch pikemen as ride, ſhall goe with their pikes in the ſame place where their maiſter vſe to marche in the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, that occaſion being offered, that the people ſhould alight and march on foote. Each ſouldier that is on horſe backe may ſpeedily returne to his place, and the ſquadron neede not to bee broken or confuſed. The very ſame ought to be obſerued by thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who though they march on foote, yet haue their men to carry their pikes: who ought to beare them hard by their Maſters in the ſame ranke or in the other ranke behinde them: wher when neceſſity is offered, the ſouldiers may take there pikes, and their men or boyes ought incontinently get themſelues out of the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron or battayl. And to tel you the truth, I like not the manner &amp; order which I haue herein don and obſerued by diuers Sergeants Maior, who placed al the ſeruants, lackeis, and boyes, together in order nere the bands either before them or behynd them. For it is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19616:19"/> moſt manifeſt that in ſo doing the ſquadron cannot ſcape confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and diſorder, and none of them that ride know their place cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely. Wheras it is moſt neceſſarie that the Sergeant Maior ſhould in nothing ſo much trouble and waſt himſelfe as in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his people to be ſo lead, that all and each of them know his owne place. For herein conſiſteth the conſeruation of all good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: when they come neare the place where they are to lodge, the Captaynes (as I haue alreadie tolde you) ought to light with in one halfe a myle at the leaſt of it, and ſo following them, the other ſouldiers that ryde, ought likewiſe to light on foote, and it is conuenient that the Sergeant Maior, eyther himſelfe, or by his aſſiſtant, ſhould be acquainted with the ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place a while before the companyes reach thyther. And comming vnto the place of armes or watch-hill of the ſayde lodging, he ought to forme a Squadron, and make his Battaile, not permitting any Souldiers to goe to his quarter, or to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranke himſelfe vntill ſuch time that the whole regiment being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued the Sergeant Maior himſelfe, or his aſſiſtaunte, commeth to the Enſignes and licence them to go to theyr lodgings. Who (as you haue ſéene) are lodged in the front of the quarters of each companyes, all of them in one ranke, and beneath them are the ſouldiers lodged. The Sergeant Maior ought not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in any caſe, that any cart or other baggage be put before the ſtandards or Enſignes, and much leſſe ought he to permitte any fire to be made there, nor any let or hinderaunce: for all a long from that place is the watch-hill, or place of armes, which ought to be kept vncombred and frée for the Squadron only. When the regiment is lodged, the Sergeant Maior ought incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cauſe a Courte-gard of fiue and twenty men to be ſet about ſeuentie or eightie paces from the front of the lodging. And theſe ſouldiers ought to be taken out of one of thoſe companyes that watched the night before: ſéeing that it appertayneth vnto them to be of the watch vntill the new watch entereth, and foure and twenty howers be expyred: ſaue only when one whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany is appointed to watch by day, and in this caſe hee ought to appoint ſome of the companyes of Arcabuzers to watch, and this Courte-garde which I ſayde to bée ſet in the daye time, ought to be in the ſame place, where at night the companye that doo enter to watch ſhall be placed. After this the firſt thing that
<pb facs="tcp:19616:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> he ought to doo, is to make himſelfe well acquainted with his quarter, and to ſée whether it be neceſſary there ſhoulde be any pathes or wayes made, that the ſouldiers may commodiouſly get out to fight: and if néede be they ſhould be made with all ſpéede, (for it oftentimes chaunceth that the companyes be lodged in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, woods, and vines, where a man cannot without much a doo get out, vnleſſe there be wayes made) it appertayneth vnto the Sergeant Maior in all haſt to cauſe wayes to be made, and paſſage to be made eaſie, and all thinges to be taken away that may any wayes hinder or let, that the ſquadron can not be made with all ſpéede and facility. And as well for this, as for the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the lodgings, and making paſſages and wayes for the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie to paſſe: there be in all armies certaine companies of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anors, ouer which the Generall of the artilery or his Liefetenant hath iuriſdiction. And the Sergeant Maior making recourſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of theſe, ought to prouide all thinges neceſſary to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. After this, if there be an whole armie, hee is to goe to the Maiſter of the Campe generall, and learne how many of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of his regiments he ſhall bring to watch, &amp; in what quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they ſhall be appointed. But if he be there alone with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment onely, hee ought to eſpie and view the place diligently, and to diſpoſe the Sentonels in ſuch maner that no man may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly enter or go foorth of the lodging or quarter, vnleſſe he be ſéene by them: and if ſo be that his regiment be with other regiments whether they be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame nation or of an other, he ought to ioyne with the Sergeant Maior of the ſayd regimentes and agrée with them of the manner and order to be vſed by them in appointing the watch, and ſending out the Sentonels, in ſo much that there be nothing neglected or left vnperfit: for all this office conſiſteth in warineſſe and diligence: and it is very watchfulnes it ſelfe. Then it appertayneth vnto the Sergeant M. to go for the watch worde vnto the generall, and to take directions for the next day, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently to beare it vnto the Colonell, &amp; to make him acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the directions which he bringeth: notwithſtanding that ſometimes the Colonell himſelfe taketh the watchword and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the generall, and giueth it to the S. Maior, but properly it concerneth the S. Maior to doo this. Furthermore the houre being come to ſet the watch (which ought not to be before the night approcheth, eſpecially if the enemy be not farre off for the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19616:20"/> Sergeant Maior ought as far as poſſible they can, to vſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo, that the enemy do not ſpy, whence they picke out thoſe that are to watch and to ſtand Sentonels) he ought to gather together the company or companies that be of the watch (which ordinarily ſhould be cauſed in the morning by the head drommer of the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be ready) and place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe parts &amp; quarters which (as I ſayde aboue) hee ought to haue eſpyed before: and he ought ſtraight to informe the Sergeants of thoſe companies where they ſhall ſend out the Sentonels, and what order they ſhall vſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the rownds: and he ought to haue an eſpeciall regarde, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes to viſite all thinges and to ouer-ſée them, noting and marking whether they be ſo doone and executed as he preſcribed &amp; ordained: and if he find any thing neglected, as well in this as all other orders and directions which he giueth the officers, he ought not to let it paſſe vnrebuked more or leſſe ſeuerally, according as the caſe requireth. For becauſe the Sergeants Maior are ſlow in rebuking and puniſhing the faultes and negligences which the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and ſouldiers oftentimes do commit, thence it commeth to paſſe that they are themſelues not ſet by, and theyr directions and orders nothing regarded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>You haue tolde me more then I aſked of you, and I am very glad that your diſcretion forgetteth not to teach mée that which by reaſon of my ignorance I know not to aſke. But now I deſire you to tell me what diſtance you thinke there ought to be betwéene the watch, and the quarters or lodgings: and how far the Sentonels ought to be ſeparated from the Courte-gardes, and how far diſtance they ought to ſtand the one from the other: and laſtly whether they ought to ſtand double or ſingle. For of all theſe things, I haue heard diuerſe opinions, and I haue ſéene thoſe things diuerſely vſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>In incamping, they vſe oftentimes to intrench the armie, and reare a ramper round about the quarters, for the greater ſafetie and ſtrength of the lodgings: and then, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes that are of the watch ought alwayes to go out to warde, and kéepe the trench, which is the wall of the lodging or campe. But in caſe there be no trench, as I tolde you aboue, I would not haue, that the Courte-guard ſhould be at the moſt, no further from the front of the lodgings then ſeuenty or eyghtye paces, in the place of armes or watch hill: how be it ſometimes they
<pb facs="tcp:19616:21"/> ſhall finde certaine motes, ditches, or gappes ſo ſtrong, that it would not be amiſſe for them to ſet the watch there, though it be ſomething ſarther from the lodging then the ſayde diſtaunce. For ſuch like defenſes ſerue in ſtéede of trenches: but in caſe there be none ſuch, then the watch ought to be ſette according to the manner aboue ſayde. Séeing that as well for the ſafety of the quarters, as to ayde and ſuccour them if neceſſity ſhould ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, it is better that the watch ſhould be ſome thing neare the companyes then farre from them. The in-moſt Sentonelles ought to ſtande no farther from the courte gards then thirtie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and there ought not to be more diſtance from the one to the other, then that they may be ſuffered by the darkeneſſe of the night to ſée one another. For the ſentonels being as it were the wall of the Campe, and ſtanding there to the end that no bodie may paſſe in or out vnleſſe he be ſeene, if they did ſtande farther one from the other, they ſhould bee deceiued of that which they entende, and fall into great inconueniences, and faultes in their watch. Theſe Sentonels as the principall and chiefeſt ought to be double. Seeing that, as it is commonly ſayde, more ſee foure eyes then two: and alſo if there bee a freſh and colde ayre, one of them may walke vp and downe, whileſt the other watcheth: and if they ſee any thing whereof they ought to aduiſe their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, one of them may go and the other ſtande ſtill, in ſo much that for all theſe cauſes it is neceſſary and more ſafe for the whole Campe, that theſe Sentonels ſhould ſtande double. But thirtie paces beyond theſe Sentonels, other Sentonels ſtand ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, which are by ſome called (though not properly) forlorne Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonels, which ought to ſtand no farther one from another then the other firſt &amp; in-moſt Sentonels: and if ſo be they ſée any thing they ought to retyre to the nearer ſentonels and aduiſing them of that which they ſawe. They ought to returne to theyr places againe without calling arme at all: but if caſe they ſee any notorious quantitie of people, eyther on horſe or on foote, then ought they to retyre to the double Sentonelles, and if they all three doo affirme that they are ſure they ſee ſuch troupes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple comming: then ought they to call arme, but not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for oftentimes eyther feare or a mans owne imagination maketh a ſmall number to ſéeme a great many vnto one man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone: and in a Camy, no man ought to call arme, but vpon great
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19616:21"/> occaſion. And to this intent the carefulneſſe and watchfulneſſe of the Officers of the companies that watch is very important, for they ought to viſit and ouerſée the watch very ordinarily and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, which likewiſe ought to be done by the Sergeant Maior euery night at ſundry houres, as well to viſit and ſée whether eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing be done according as it was ordeined, as alſo becauſe this may be a chiefe cauſe to moue the Officers and Souldiers to looke to their charge, knowing that they ſhall be viſited and ouerſéene by the Sergeant Maior at diuers times, and rebuked and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for theyr negligence and faults if ſo be they commit any. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in Court-gards eſpecially in the night-time is verie neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I meane, that all noiſe, ſtirre, cries, and hollowings, ought to be quite expelled from the watch, and if they talke one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ought to ſpeake low &amp; ſoftly, with modeſty. but the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonels ought not to ſpeake at any time, but alwaies to be not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie verie watchfull in ſéeing and looking, but alſo verie attentiue in harkening: for verie many times they may chaunce to heare that which by reaſon of the darkeneſſe of night, they cannot by ſight perceiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me, why you ſaid that ſome men improperly call the outtermoſt Sentinelles that ſtand ſingle, forlorne Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe (properly he is called a forlorne Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, that neceſſitie ſo requiring) is ſet either on foote or horſebacke neare to the enemies Camp, to giue aduiſement whether any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple gone forth of the Camp, or whether the Camp depart ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and this Sentinell ought to bee ſo neare the Camp of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that if hee be cfpied, hee may harlie eſcape, and returne with great difficultie: and ought not to bee ſent, but when they haue great neceſſitie of ſuch aduiſements, and ſo this Sentinell ought not to haue the watchword of our Camp, for the inconuenience which might come, if he ſhould be taken by the enemy, and being bribed, ſhould let them know our watchword: but hee ought to haue a different and particuler counter-token for himſelfe onely, by which he may be knowne and receiued at his returne. As for the vtmoſt Sentinels, that ſtand ſingle by themſelues before the double Sentinels, I know not vpon what reaſon ſome call them forlorne Sentinels: ſéeing that they ſtanding but thirtie paces from the double Sentinels, may (ſufficient cauſe why they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19616:22"/> doo it being offered) commodiouſly retire backe to the double Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels, and ſo as well the one as the other (if they bee forced by neceſſitie) may ſpéedely repayre to the Courte-gard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Thinke you that the Sentinels when there is an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme in the Camp, ought all of them to returne to their Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>In no caſe, if their Corporall cauſe them not to retire: ſéeing that they may not ſtirre from the place appointed them, without the leaue of their Corporall: thoſe Sentinels ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted that call arme, and ſpie the ſury of their enemy ruſhing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and be not able to reſiſt it: theſe may and ought to retire to their Courte-gard, but all the reſt ought to ſtand firmely, and kéepe their places. And ſéeing that I haue reſolued you of the doubt you were in, and what I thinke the Sentinels ought to do, I will alſo tell you what I remember of thoſe companies that watch. For oftentimes (as you haue ſéene) thrée or foure compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of one regiment are appointed to watch in one night. Now, if it ſhould chance that there ſhould be an allarme in the Camp, it were not conuenient that each company ſhould make a ſquadron apart, but that they ſhould méet <note n="*" place="margin">Whereas he ſpeaketh that all the companies ought to make one ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, I vnderſtand him, all of them that are appointed to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aim<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Courtegard, for if he meane that all the pettie Courts de gard ſhall reuert and make one maine ſtand, then muſt hee needes leaue much of the Cople to ſpoile, beſides cut himſelfe for intelligence, and ſo not know where to anſwere his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the beſt aduantage.</note> altogither by the maine Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegard, which place beeing the place of Armes is more commodious, and they ought to be appointed before, by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior there to make their Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron: whether alſo all the reſt that are in their quarters ſhall aſſemble and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther togither: but marke, that thoſe companies which watch either by the Captaine Generall, or by the Municion houſe, or out of the place of Armes, or out of their quarters, ought <note n="*" place="margin">It is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to allow that anie watch may be without ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinell.</note> not to ſend out theyr Sentinels: and when it happeneth ſo that there be an allarme in the Camp, the Sergeant Maior, (whoſe Squadron being made before all things, all the time the allarme continueth, doth kéepe his ward) ought to know and vnderſtand the cauſe of the allarme very well and ſurely: and it being knowne vnto him, he ought to aduiſe his neighbour regiments of it, and eſpecially his Captaine Generall, and the Maiſter of the field, without whoſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement (I meane the Captaine Generall) the companies that are ſet in Battaile, ought not to returne to their wardes or quarters:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19616:22"/> but after the Sergeant Maior is ſure that they may ſafely doo it, and haue licenſe of the Captaine Generall, hée may ſend out the Sentinels againe, and appoint them their places as before: and if ſo be that he thinke it neceſſary, to encreaſe the force of the watch, he may do it with more Souldiers or leſſe, according as the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the time requireth. Furthermore, ſeeing that we now ſpeak of the watch and Sentinels, or ſhield watch, I will aduertiſe you of an ordinary and great negligence, which is committed as well by the vnſhilfull and vnapt Officers, as common Souldiers in the maner of aſking and demanding the watchword one of the other, and alſo in giuing it one to the other: which being one of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt things in warfare that ought to be done, with due regard and conſideration, is now leaſt regarded, and therefore I could wiſh, that euerie one ſhould be carefull of this, béeing a matter of ſuch waight and moment: and that the Round, when he viſiteth the Sentinell, if he finde him watchfull according to his dutie, he née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not at <note n="*" place="margin">If he may come ſo neare the Sentinell as to ſee whether hee doo his duetie or not without any triall, ſo may hee likewiſe come being an enemy, and ſpie how the Court of gards be placed, or for ſome other intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and ſo go his way againe without ſaying any thing.</note> euery time to come neare him, but paſſe to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sentinels: and if hee finde them all awake and doing theyr dutie, he ought to returne to the courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard. And in ſuch a caſe I thinke it not neceſſary, that the watchword ſhould be giuen from one ſide to the other, ſéeing that the Round commeth not neare the Sentinels. And when vpon ſome neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary occaſion, the Round commeth neare to the Sentinels, then ought the Sentinell or ſhield-watch (if hee be an Hargabuzer put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his match into the cocke of his péece, and if he be a pikeman trailing his Pike) demand the watchword: and that no further of, that it may be heard with a low voice, and after the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ought the Round to giue the watch word vnto the Sentinell, who in no caſe ought to ſuffer any man to come néere him, vnleſſe he giue him the watchword, although he know him to be his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine or Sergeant Maior, or maiſter of the camp: for the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier being appointed Sentinell, is not <note n="*" place="margin">In this matter is ther a queſtion, for as wel may the Sentinel forget the watchword, wherof may enſue many deſperate caſual ties, as alſo be negligent in other duties. I think it therfore neceſſary, that the Captain of the watch, or the Sergeant Maior, either by an ordinary time of Round, or els by ſome certain token ray be known to the ſentinell, that therby he may proue the ſentence in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his duetie, otherwiſe the Sentinell hauing forgotten the watchword, ſhall haue it brought him by the next Round, or otherwiſe may let a falſe round, or kill a true round, &amp;c.</note> bound to know any man,
<pb facs="tcp:19616:23"/> or to let him come neare him, except he giue him the watchword. For we ſée daily, that men bee eaſily deceiued in theſe two ſenſes of hearing and ſéeing. And for this cauſe is it nowe vſed in warfare, that all the wardes receiue a countertoken or ſigne of the Captaine generall (which the Italians called <hi>Moto,</hi> and the Spaniards <hi>Nombre,</hi> but in England it is called the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word) to exclude all ſuſpicion and deceit, and that wee may know aſſuredly, that hee who giueth vs ſuch a token or ſigne, is one of our Camp, and that we may ſafely let him come neare vs as our friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Yet I doubt of one thing by reaſon of that which you ſaid but a while ſince. For I haue euer heard that the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell ought not to let any man paſſe vnles he giue the watchword: how ſay you then that the Round, if he finde the Sentinell wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching according to their duetie, after he hath ſéene them, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Courtegard without giuing the watchword.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Know that the Sentinell ought not to let any of the Camp to go in or out vnleſſe he giue the watchword, much leſſe ought hee to let him come neare the place where hee himſelfe ſtandeth: but if the Round or Captaine of the watch paſſe eight or tenne paces from him, it is ſufficient that they ſpeake, neither is it neceſſary that they ſhould be bound to giue the watchword, and this is to be vnderſtood, if the Round or Captaine of the watch paſſe within the watch hill: for if hee paſſe two or fro without the Camp, then ought not the Sentinell, to ſuffer him come neare for to know him, though he be no farther of then the ſaid diſtance, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he giue the watchword, and if chance he giue it not, he may ſlea him as an enemy, beſides, note that though he that commeth from abroad out of the Camp giue the watchword, yet ought not the Sentinell fréely to let him enter in the Lodge, but he ought to accompany him vnto the double Sentinels, and charge them with him, that one of them in like maner, may go with him to the main Courte-gard, and deliuer him to the Sergeant, Enſigne, or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the company, who are bound incontinently to aduiſe the Sergeant Maior of it, and it appertaineth vnto him to bring him to the maiſter of the Camp, or Captaine Generall if néed be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you of the litle Courte-gards, which I haue ſéen ſome Sergeants Maiors take out of the maine Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards, where thoſe Sentinels and companies be in, that watch in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19616:23"/> the outward parts of the Camp: what thinke you of them? are you of opinion that they be neceſſarie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Certes, I thinke that who ſo doth, cannot doo amiſſe, and I haue ſeene it vſed very much, and the true cauſe why this is vſed, is this, ſuch courtegards are taken onely of thoſe Souldiers, that are appointed for Sentinels and Roundes that night: to the end that the Officer or Corporall at the time when he is to change them, may finde them more readily: theſe courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards ſerue alſo, that the Sentinels, (occaſion being offered) might haue helpe and aide with more ſpéed, and they furthermore, cauſe the watch to be more vigilant and watchfull. And all whatſoeuer ſerueth to make a Souldier, more viligent and ready for the ſeruice of their companies and to diſcharge their dutie ought to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and approued as good and profitable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you ſir, ought the watch to retire from theyr ward in the morning, without expecting or looking for any other order.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>No: but euen as they were appointed to watch by the Sergeant Maior, ſo may they not return without his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, for he is bound him ſelfe or his aſſiſtant to come and releaſe them, and ſet the others whoſe turne it is to watch by day. And ſéeing it commeth to the purpoſe, you ſhall vnderſtand, that the companies being ſet in the watch or in battaile, or lodged in theyr quarters, or embarked in ſhips, when they are in ſeruice, then may none of them ſtir or paſſe out of the place appointed them (obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſuch diſcipline as ought to be vſed in warfare) vnleſſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior giue order for it. Neither ought the Maiſter or chiefe heads of the Campe, giue any ſuch order vnto the companies, or commaund them any thing, but by the meanes of the Sergeant Maior, who is the guide, key &amp; inſtrument of all ſuch commands, iniunctions, and proclamations, which the Captains General and maiſters of the Camp cauſe to be made vnto their companies, and ſo likewiſe without his licenſe ought no Generall or particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, command, or proclamation, to be made in his Regiment. And if there be any Municion of Powder, Match, Leade, Victuals <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r weapons, prouided for the Regiment, (all which ought to be ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be brought by the chiefe Furrire or Commiſſary, if there be one) it apperteineth vnto the Sergeant to part &amp; diuide it among the companies. And alſo the Sergeant Maior is the Generall and
<pb facs="tcp:19616:24"/> onely procurer of the welfare of all the Souldiers, for it appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto him to ſolicitate that they be prouided of all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as when they are without weapons, or want Municion, or victuals, to make ſute vnto the Generall and chiefe of the camp, that they may haue it: and if they be not well paid and want mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hauing great néed of it, he is to ſpeake vnto the maiſter of the Camp and to the Generall, to prouide their pay, and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſicke or hurt, or ſorely wounded in the Camp, he ought to cauſe them to be carried very carefully to the Hoſpitals and places ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that intent, prouiding them of Cartes, baggages and Waggons (if it bee neceſſarie) and to doo all this, hee is to haue the helpe of all the Officers in his Regiment, who ought to ayde and obey him. For hee vſeth the Captaine of the fielde to ſée the Cartes and baggages that are neceſſarie for the Regiments, and alſo guides for the wayes. When they are to march ſome iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, the chiefe Furrire ſtandeth the Sergeant Maior in ſtead, to bring Municion and victuals: and the Sergeants to lead the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in good order, &amp; in thoſe things that apperteine to the watch, he vſeth the Enſigne: and ſheweth him what order he will haue obſerued for the ſeruice of the companies: and the Drumme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior ſerues to proclaime the generall commandes and Edicts, and aduiſes the Captaines that are to watch. But aboue all things it is neceſſarie that the Sergeant Maior ſhould haue an aſſiſtant to helpe him, with whom he ſhould (with the will of the counſell and chiefe of the camp) communiate his power and authoritie: of whom the Captaines and Officers of the Regiment ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the order to be obſerued, &amp; obey him as the Sergeant Maior himſelfe. And therefore it is requiſite, that he ſhould be a very ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient man, welbeloued &amp; well known, left he loſe the credit &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, which hée ought to haue in reſpect of the Office which he beareth, for want of thoſe parts and qualities that are required in ſuch like perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>You haue ſatiſfied me of many things that I had in my minde ready to aſke of you: but beſides the reſt, I would now requeſt you to tell me, of whom the Sergeant Maior, is to take the watch-word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Of the Captaine Generall, Coronell, or Maiſter of the camp onely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>And put the caſe, that ſome Captaine remaine Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19616:24"/> ouer the companies of his Regiments, as it daily falleth out, ought the Sergeant Maior to take the watch-word of him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Ought then the Sergeant Maior to giue it himſelf?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>London.</speaker>
               <p>No: for it apperteineth to the gouernor to giue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Why then vnto whom doth it appertain to aſke it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>The Serg. Maior his aſſiſtant ought to go to the gouernor to fetch it, &amp; incontinently to bring it to the Ser. Maior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>And if it chance hee hath not any aſſiſtant (as moſt times they haue none,) who ſhall take it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Then it apperteineth vnto the Sergeant of the company that is to watch, to go &amp; take it, &amp; bring it to the S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior himſelfe onely for to obſerue. The honor and preheminence due to an Office of ſo great authoritie, as the Office which the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior beareth, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as in our former diſcourſe) you haue béen certified the Captains receiue the orders by them to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, it is not decent, much leſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, that the ſergeant Maior ſhould go to take the watchword of any one but his ſuperior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you ſir, is it not more eſtéemed &amp; of more credit, for one to be Captaine, then a Serg Maior: ſéeing that to reward him, they vſe to giue him a band company of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>Of this the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, of happy memory, marueiled, and not without great reaſon: for one <hi>Villan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drando</hi> a Serg. Maior, in the ſeruice done at <hi>Dura,</hi> comming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to aſke a certaine company of him, that had béen vacant: making more account to be captaine of the ſame, then of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he did beare, the Emperor anſwered, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the office of a S. Maior was far more preeminent, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> order preſcribed vnto them by the S. Maior, &amp; taketh directions by the Generall, or of the King or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror himſelf: &amp; in war the S. Maior is barred from no place, but he may fréely enter into the Pauilion, or chamber of the king, or Generall. <hi>Villandrando,</hi> anſwered his Maieſtie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had reaſon, but that it was of old vſed among y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Spaniſh footemen, that the S. Maior ſhould in reward, be made captaine of ſome company, by reaſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wages or ſtipend giuen to the S. Maior was ſo ſmall and miſerable. And for this cauſe, verie well doe the Germans, Italians, and Frenchmen, alwaies chooſe one of the beſt and moſt ſufficient Captains, to bear this Office: and ſo they are both
<pb facs="tcp:19616:25"/> Captaines and Sergeant Maior together: and in the abſence of their Coronell or Maiſter of the Camp (by the law of war) it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth vnto them in their ſtead to gouern the bands or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their regiments: and ſurely they doo very wiſely: and the Spaniards onely cannot yet conſider it, whence grow many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, for we ſée that verie many are choſen to exerciſe the Office of a Sergeant Maior, that are very vnapt, inſufficient, and vnſkilfull (as we haue noted in the beginning of this diſcourſe:) and becauſe they haue not that authoritie and power which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in ſuch a charge, it falleth out oftentimes that the Captains ſet nought by them, whereas if they were Captaines of a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beſides as well as they, they would not contemne them: and alſo, Captaines doo more willingly obey and receiue the order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by another Captaine as they bee, then of him that is but Sergeant Maior, and who (as they know) aſpireth to bee made Captaine of a bande of men, in reward of his ſeruice. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I thinke it be ſomething late, and I beléeue we haue runne through all the chiefeſt points concerning this Office, that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary well to diſcharge it, let vs turne ouer the land, that ſéeing we haue walked ſomething farre by reaſon of this delectable and pleaſant Riuer, before wée returne I may tell you, what I thinke the Sergeant Maior ought to doo, when he with his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment entereth into ſome place or Fortreſſe to lie in Garriſon, and herewith wée will cloſe vp our diſcourſe to day, But firſt I will tell you, that ſéeing the Sergeant Maior is to take order and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of ſo many and waightie matters, and that hée is to make prouiſion of ſo many thinges: and ſéeing that hée ought to be ſo vigilant and quicke in ouerſéeing and diſcharging the one, and in prouiding for the other: hée ought when hée goeth to the field to be well prouided of good Nagges. And know, that he onely is allowed at all times and in all partes, and vpon what occaſion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, to croſſe vp and downe the Squadrons and Battailes of the Army on Horſe backe: yea althogh hée goe to the Captaine Generall to fetch the watchword: and if it chaunce he bee ſéene on Horſebacke, it ought not to be imputed to ill or vntowardly bringing vp, neither is he bounde to go on foote, as ſome vnfit and ſottiſhe Seargeant Mayor doe, for the carefulneſſe and ſpéedineſſe, neceſſarie in his charge requireth ſuch prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence. And in the daye, that is appointed for the battayle,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19616:25"/> ought he much leſſe to be on foote, and place himſelfe in the ranke among the other Captaynes, as ſome be perſwaded hee ought to doo: ſéeing that he fighting there can ſtande in ſtead but of one: whereas if he be on horſebacke he may ſerue for many, ouerſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prouiding for many things that at ſuch times chance to be neceſſary and which often are cauſe of the victorie: and becauſe no particular thing appertayning vnto this office that I remember, ſhall eſcape vnſpoken of, I will not paſſe with ſilence (becauſe I haue ſéene many ignorant fellowes take it in digeon) how that the Sergeants Maior ordinarily beare a ſhort ſticke ſomething thicke in their hand, which ſerueth them for very many vſes: as well to ſeparate horſes one from an other, and cauſe other bagga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be remooued &amp; ſet a ſide, which oftentimes do much harme to the rankes and ſquadrons, cauſing confuſion, as to ſhew and point certaine things which they commaund, vſing it as wee vſe our foorefinger <hi>Index,</hi> when we ſhowe or point at any thing: and they vſe alſo at the inſtant and preſent time to correct and puniſh the diſobedience of ſome ſouldiers with this cudgell: which no man ought to be aſhamed of, or thinke himſelfe iniured or abuſed, and he is a very ignorant fellowe that will take it in dugeon, for euen ſo both the Maiſter of the campe, the Captaynes and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants Maior with ſuch a ſticke or leading ſtaffe vſe to correct the ſouldiers, and oftentimes breake it on his head that is ſtubborne and will not obay, going out of order contrary to the captayne or Sergeant Maior his direction, and it is very well done, ſéeing it is done to puniſh them for their vnrulineſſe. Furthermore this leading ſtaffe is ordinarily the Sergeant Maior his wepon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he iuſtly puniſheth the faults of his ſouldiers, and would to God all thoſe vnreaſonable and brutiſh corrections were baniſhed out of the warres, which many Officers doo with their ſwordes and holberds, wounding their men &amp; breaking their limmes, yea and alſo killing many of them for very ſmall faults, and vpon lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle occaſion, which ought not to be doone, but in caſes of notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſobedience, and vnleſſe it were neceſſarily required for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe worthy reſpects that they ſhould be puniſhed in <hi>fraganti.</hi> We haue made an end of all things that ſéeme vnto me to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for a Sergeant Maior to exerciſe his office in the field, now will we paſſe on forwards and entreate of thoſe things which hée ought to doo, when he entereth into ſome fortreſſe or campe with
<pb facs="tcp:19616:26"/> his companies to lodge there, and to appoint the watch for the ſafe defence of the ſame, and therfore I ſay, that when a regiment lyeth in garriſon in ſome place, and is to remaine there ſome daies for to kéepe the ſame, the firſt thing that the Sergeant Maior ought to doo, is to make himſelfe acquainted with the place both within and without, vewing each part and parcell thereof, and conſidering which partes are moſt neceſſary and commodious for to place the Courte-gardes and Sentonelles or ſhield-watch, and alſo wherethe rowndes may be appointed to goe in the night time to ouerſée the Sentonelles: hee ought likewiſe to marke what place may bee moſt fitte for the place of armes or watch-hill, where if chance there ſhould be an allarum, the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers might aſſemble and gather together: and this being done, he ought to diuide &amp; quarter out his companies according as he ſhall thinke it néedefull or requiſite for the ſafe defence of that place and of this partition which he maketh (firſt of all communicating it vnto the Maiſter of the Camp) he ſhall giue his enſigne an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſigned with his name in writing, to the end that none of the Officers may with reaſon excuſe himſelfe, if any negligence or careleſneſſe be committed by them touching the watch, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then was ordayned or appointed them, ſéeing they had it ſet downe in writing. The Seargeant Maior muſt bee aduiſed that he ought to be very circumſpect and warie in parting his companyes, and ſetting the watch in a Fortreſſe or Campe, eſpecially if it happen ſo that the enemie haue his Campe not farre off (how ſo euer warineſſe, watchfulneſſe, and diligence is very neceſſarie at all times in this profeſſion) and ſo he muſt take héede that hee commit not that errour and ouerſight that manie Seargeantes Maior doo in deuiding the watch of the place by quarters, appointing each companie theyr quarter, my meaning is that hee ſhould not appoint each companye a part of the wall or rampier, ordinarily to keepe and defende the ſame: ſéeing that for the moſt part that anie Fortreſſe, Citie, Towne, Caſtle or Campe, hath béene taken or aſſaulted by charge, the cauſe thereof hath béene, that the Corporall or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonell being bribed, did knowe the place or quarter in which it appertayned vnto him ordinarily to watch. And I could make a true rehearſall in teſtimonie héereof, of thoſe thinges which I haue my ſelfe ſéene paſſed in the warre of <hi>Sena,</hi> I beeing my
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19616:26"/> ſelfe in proper perſon called as a witneſſe to the ſelfe ſame matter which I meane here to declare, which was thus: <hi>Don Garcia de Toledo,</hi> who (was Generall of the armie by reaſon of the death of his father <hi>Don Pedio de Toledo</hi> Uiceroy) beſeiging <hi>Montalehin,</hi> a certayne Sergeant of the Duke of <hi>Soma,</hi> and a Corporall a very friende of his, both of them baniſhed out of the kindgome of <hi>Naples,</hi> being appointed and charged alwayes to watch one ſelfe ſame place &amp; quarter of the wall, occaſion ſeruing them, they offered <hi>Don Garcia de Toledo,</hi> that they would let him with all the forces that he would bring thether, enter into the place, by that quarter &amp; part of the wall which was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto theyr ward: and as this treaſon was euen concluded, it fell out that at the ſame inſtant one <hi>Iordanus Vrfenus,</hi> (who was at the defence of <hi>Montalehin</hi>) ordayned as a vigilant and carefull man (how be it the rumour runned that it was doone by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Captaine <hi>Moretus,</hi> who was alſo at the ſame time within that place with his companye) that the watch ſhoulde no more bee ſette by appointing each companie their quarter in which they ordinarily ſhoulde watch, during the time of theyr beeing there, as they had doone thether to, but that all the companyes that were appointed to watch gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the place of armes, ſhould caſt lots for the places and quarters in which each one ſhoulde watch, ſo that afterwarde the foreſayde Seargeant and Corporall béeing vnſure of the place where they ſhoulde watch, could not bring their treaſon to effect, which in a very fewe dayes after chaunced to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by fault of one of their ſeruauntes, ſo that they were therefore executed, and hanged by the féete on the tappe of the wall, as all they that were in that ſeruice and place ſalue, and as I beléeue will remember it. Therefore the Seargeant Maior ought not onely to ordayne that the companyes that are appoynted to watch ſhoulde caſt lottes euerie night, to ſee whoſe lott it chaunceth to bee to watch in this or that quarter or part of the wall, but following the right order, it is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and neceſſarie that the Squadron and Sentonelles ſhoulde doo the ſame, ſo that neyther the Squadrons knowe their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor the companyes what part of the wall they ſhall kéepe, nor the Sentonelles much leſſe what place they ſhall ſtande in before the very houre that the watch is ſet. Neyther is there
<pb facs="tcp:19616:27"/> any cauſe why any Officer or ſouldier ſhoulde take this in duge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, imagining that they be but little truſted, and that their fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and faithfulneſſe is had in queſtion: for wee knowe that in all congregations and companyes that were moſt faithfull and true to theyr Princes and common-weales, there haue neuer béene baſe mindes wanting, who being eyther enduced by luker, or ouercome with ſome humaine paſſion, haue made ſale of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Prouinces, and Kingdomes. Beſides this, no Nation that maintaineth warre ought in this age to be more carefull and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then the Spaniſh, ſéeing we knowe how odious it is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto all other countryes, becauſe they haue euer ſince foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares hitherward, maintayned warres ordinarily for the ſeruice of their king in moſt partes of <hi>Europe:</hi> and ſéeing that it is moſt certayne, that among the bandes and companyes of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſouldiers, there be many ſtraungers that ſerue among them, as <hi>Italians, Germans, Frenchmen, Fleminges, Engliſhmen,</hi> and <hi>Burgunnians,</hi> who ſeruing and being brought vp among the Spaniards from their youth, learne to ſpeake the ſpaniſh tongue ſo perfectly, that it is impoſſible to diſcerne many of them from naturall Spaniards: and of theſe, many (as by experience wee haue béene taught) haue often attempted foule and filthy practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in ſo much that all the care which in this caſe is taken, is moſt iuſtlye taken and with great reaſon, and wee ought to bee verie ſcrupulous and curious herein, which our curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and warineſſe ought to be allowed, and approoued of vs all to be moſt profitable, good, and neceſſarie, for no mans credite is thereby diminiſhed or any whitt empayred, but the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie and occaſion of treaſon is taken from them that beare diſloyall and trayterous mindes, and herewithall, all they that lye in garriſon, are moſt ſafe from daunger, and ſure of their liues, and the kinges ſeruice is accordingly looked vnto. But to returne to our purpoſe: the Sergeant Maior hauing diuided his men according to the manner aforeſayde, hee is to regarde, whether the Courte-gardes into which the companie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes are to enter, or they that watch at the gates, or the horſemen: whether the ſayde Courte-gardes be commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or fitte for the turne, or lacke reparation, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whether the Sentinell houſe where the Sentinels muſt ſtande, bee well placed and can reſiſt againſt the ſtormes of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19616:27"/> raine and winde, and if chaunce they be ruinous and weather bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the Sergeant Maior ought to cauſe them to be repaired with all ſpeede at the coſte of the countrey as by cuſtome is vſed, hee ought alſo to conſider whether the rounds may eaſely paſſe round about the walls, and if there be any difficulty, he ought inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to cauſe the paſſage to be made eaſey. Furthermore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion is to be made of lampes and lanternes as wel for the court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, as for the rownds and countre roundes. As for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies that are of the watch, the Sergeants Maior vſe to ſet them at different houres, the one party in the morning, the other at night, and ſometims later then at other times, as they think good, but according to my minde (if neceſſity conſtrayned me not to doe otherwiſe) I would alwayes ſet the watch an hower before Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſette: that the ſouldier may come to the watch after ſupper, and ſo ſhal he haue no occaſion to goe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the watch, after he is come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and before the gates be ſhut vp, no man ought to be vnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for leauing aſide how neceſſary carefulnes and watchfulnes is in ſuch caſes, it it likewiſe needefull that the ſouldiers ſhould bée taught and made to vnderſtand how filthy and alienate it is from their profeſſion to doe as they doe. Viz. that as ſoone as they are entered in to the court guarde, incontinently they hang vp theyr weapons on the walles, vnarming themſelues preſently, and this licentiouſnes is ſo farre come, that not onely in places where they lie in garriſon, but in the field alſo, and when they haue an oppoſite army iuſt ouer againſt them, they doe the very ſame, which ought in no caſe to be permitted. For no ſouldier ought to be ſuffered to vnarme himſelfe before he ſeeth his anſigne to doſſe his armour, on whome they ought to caſt their eies to imitate him, as they doe on the ſtandard which he beareth to follow him, in ſo much that the anſignes ought to be very circumſpect in their ſeruice, that the ſouldier may not take example by them of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and careleſſenes, but rather may by imitating them becom painfull and diligent. For this profeſſion is chiefely maintayned by continuall exerciſe. To conclude, great care ought to be had at the opening and ſhutting vppe of the gates, ſéeing that at ſuch times great occaſion of daunger may eaſely bee offered. For which the Sergeant Maior ought to appoint the ſergeant or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants that watch to bee preſent, at the opening and ſhutting of the gates, with their men well armed, and none of them ought to
<pb facs="tcp:19616:28"/> be ſuffered to haue his cloake about him, or any other thing that may hinder him, or be troubleſome vnto him. And firſt let foure or ſixe ſouldiers of the company goe forth through the wickets of the gates of the cities, and looke whether al be well, walking thrée or foureſcore paces from the gates, and if all be frée from daunger and in ſafety, then let the gates be opened, and firſt let them of the citty paſſe out, not in cluſters, but by little and little, one by one, but eſpecially if there be cartes or baggage to goe forth, and til all they be paſt, that goe out of the cittie, none ought to be ſuffered to paſſe in, no, not ſo much as to come neare the gates, when they be all forth that are to goe out of the gates, then after the ſame manner may they enter, that will goe into the cittye, and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary that at euery gate there be one with a long pike of y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, that if any carte paſſe by with hay or ſtrawe he may paſſe it through with his iron pike, to know whether there be no fraude or trechery, ſéeing that <hi>Caeſar</hi> of Naples in thoſe cartes which he would haue to goe to Turin, aduiſed vs that a fortreſſe, caſtle, or citty, might eaſily be gotten by ſuch <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ights. In all court guards the Sergeant Maior ought to command two Sentinels to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed both day and night, one for the weapones, the other for the fielde. Furthermore prouiſion of wood ought to bee made at at times, for though in ſommer time it be not neceſſary againſte cold, yet there ought to be fier to kindle the matches, greate care ought to be had that ther be ſome commodious place in the court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards to hang vppe the corſlets, and where all the gunnes maye lie in good order, for this is not onely neceſſary that if chaunce there be an alarme on the ſuddayne, each ſouldier may with more ſnéede finde his weapon, but alſo to ſhunne confuſion, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue due order in the courte-guard, which is an ornament vnto it. The Sergeant Maior ſhoulde not ſuffer any one in the court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to play at tables or dice, when the companies of the watch enter in, for that ſéemeth to be very vncomely and vndecent, and it is a token of contempte and diſdaine, as little reſpecting thoſe that come in, and ſetting nought by them, for ſeeyng the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies repreſent the authority of the King, the ſouldiers are bounde to receiue them in all places, all armour and noiſe ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged, yea quite baniſhed out of the courte-guard, rounde and counter round, if any one of them that watch picke a quarell or make any braulle in the court-guard, either in word or deede, hee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19616:28"/> ought to be ſeuerely puniſhed, becauſe ſuch a company being toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there might that ſoone be ſet on fire, which would not in haſt be extinguiſhed. The round and countre rounds may be of more or leſſe people, and continue more long or ſhortly, according as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity requireth, but they may neuer returne to the company af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be gone forth, til their turn be ended, which they ought to ſpend in going vp and downe about the wall, viſiting and ouerſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the watchfulneſſe of thoſe that ſtand Sentinell. The very ſame ought they to doe that are rounds in the fielde, and becauſe ſometimes it is thought to be doubtfull, in caſe the rounde meete with the vpper round, either in the fielde or where they lie in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, whither of the two ought firſt to giue the watchword, and vppon this pointe there be diuers opinions, and many moue this doubt, making an Elephant of a Flie, framing a queſtion <hi>De La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacaprina,</hi> (as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayeth) I ſay that the vpper rounds moſt commonly be of officers, and ſo according to reaſon, and due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, it is more iuſt that the round ſhould geue place, and giue the name firſt vnto the vpper rounde, but becauſe Captaynes doe alſo vſe to rounde in the ordinary turnes, to the end that no man may iuſtly take any thing in dugeon or be grieued, and to take al occaſion of doubt, and inconuenience, the Sergeant Maior (vnto whoſe charge it is committed to diſpoſe and appointe the watch rounds, and vpper rounds) ought to leaue order with the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies how they ought to doe as concerning this point, which ought to be ſuch, that the round ſhall alwayes giue place vnto the vpper round, and geue the watchword firſt, and for this cauſe the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the companies ſhould be alwaies appointed to be of the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per round as by cuſtome it is vſed. And if chaunce that there bee officers in both the rounds, or none in either of them, but they be all ſouldiers, yet howſoeuer, it is greate reaſon that the rounde ſhould geue place and giue the watchword firſt. Seeing that the vpper rounds are of more preheminence, for they are not onely appointed to doe the ſame which the rounds doe, to wit, to regard whether the court-gard and they that ſtand Sentinel do their duty or not, but alſo to ſee whether the rounds them ſelues faile not of their duty. But you muſt know that this which we haue ſaid is to be vnderſtood, in caſe that the vpper rounds be ordinary, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds are, for when the Maſter of the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p or gouernor of the place wher they lie in garriſon, or the Sergeant Maior round extraordinarily
<pb facs="tcp:19616:29"/> (as they ſometimes doe) then it appertayneth vnto them to giue the watchword. Firſt: for the round not knowing that there is any vpper round, is not bound to giue the watchword vnto anye one, but to the Sentonel, and he is to knowe and aske the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word of all them that he méeteth, and examine them what they are, and what they doe there, taking them that he findeth guilty, or going about any harme, and all other ſuſpicious perſons that he chaunceth to méete withall. Furthermore before we paſſe from this pointe, I would you ſhould be aduertiſed of an error (which is not very ſmall) and it is committed ordinarily, by reaſonof the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence and careleſſnes of the officers, and I lay this fault of this abuſe onely vpon the officers, for it is moſt manifeſt that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers do as they are taught to doe by the officers, and the abuſe is, that when one ſtandeth Sentonell, if another ſouldier come to him to haue him away, he doth not onely leaue his place, but alſo if chaunce that the other ſouldier haue not the watchword the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonell him ſelfe giueth it vnto him, and ſo doing, hee committeth all theſe faults following. Firſt he doth il becauſe as we haue ſaid, that no ſouldier ſtanding Sentonel, ought to ſuffer any one to com neare him without giuing the watchword. Secondly hee is too blame, in that he himſelf giueth the watchword vnto him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, whereas the Sentonell ought not to giue the watchworde vnto any one whatſoeuer. Thirdly he doth contrary to his duety in leauing his place and ceaſing to ſtand Sentonell, before the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer vnto whom it appertayneth to take him thence, commeth in proper perſon to renue him. But the negligence and ſmall regard of the officers, who loth to take the paines to riſe them ſelues to remoue the Sentinels (as they are bound to do it) are cauſe of theſe abuſes, and haue brought in this naughty cuſtome, that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant or Corporall towards night, name foure ſouldiers to ſtand Sentinel in one place, leauing order that when one hath ſtood out his turn, ſhould cal the other, and that they ſhould communicate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> watchword, and giue it one to another among themſelues, which ought not in any caſe to be don, for it is moſt iuſt that the officers ſhould perform that which apertaineth vnto them to do according as they are bound by their offices, and he that doth not ſo, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of his office which hee beareth, and ought to bee put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his office, and beſides this, the watchword being the ſafety and truſt of the watch of the campe of garriſon, it ought with great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19616:29"/> regarde and diſcretion bee giuen by the Seargeant Maior to the Seargeant, and of them to the Corporall and Sentinels, and ſo (due order obſerued) the Seargeant Maior ought not to giue the watchword in the field, before the Sentinels be ſent out: and when he lieth in gariſon in anie place, he ought not to giue it before the gate be ſhut vp. Neither ought the Sergeants nor Corporals giue it to the Sentinels before the verie inſtant that they bee ſent out. And note that if chance anie one be ſent forth by night (as ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it happeneth to be neceſſarie) the Seargeant Maior ought to cauſe the watchword which was appointed for the watche to bee chaunged for diuerſe inconueniences that might fall out by not ſo doing. Now after all theſe things are orderly appointed, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant Maior ought at ſundrie times and diuerſe houres to viſite them, and ſée how they be looked vnto, finding falt with them that are blame worthie, and puniſhing them that deſerue correction. The Sergeant Maior ought alwayes to be perſonally preſent in the watch, hauing great regard what number of men ſerue in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Companie, according to the muſtre which they make. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Muſter maſter or Treſurer ought to make faith vnto the Seargeant Maior. Who (if ſo be that he can find or perceiue that the Companies receiue paie for more men then they watch with) ought to make the Officers of the companies to giue him account of it: for oftentimes many ſouldiers by reaſon of theyr Officers negligence become careleſſe, and ſo they regarde not theyr duetie. They ought not to permit at the entering or departing of the watch, that the Corſlets ſhould want anie péece of their armour, or the Harguebuzer come without his head péece, and much leſſe, that they ſhould ſerue with ruſtie weapons, or notoriouſly ill gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, nor the pikes without arminges, ſeeing that it is not onely a great ornament vnto a Squadron to haue all the pikes with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, but it maketh the ſquadron to ſéeme greater, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie important circumſtance. For al ſhewes that are likely to cauſe a terror or feare to the enemies, ought to be eſteemed and greatlie accounted of. When the Companies of the watch enter into the place of Armes, it is ordinarily vſed, that the Gunne-men beeing come to the place (who vſe to march in the vantgard towarde the Court-gard) ſhould parte and open, making a lane for the Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to enter, vauncing theyr Pikes as ſoone as they come neere
<pb facs="tcp:19616:30"/> the Harguebuzerie. But I do not like this manner, for the watch to enter, for to march vauncing theyr pikes, is no time neceſſary in warres, and in ſo doing the ſouldiers exerciſe themſelues in things not neceſſarie. Therefore they ought to ſhunne the abſurdities which you ſée the Corſlets ordinarily commit in ſtepping backe, when they vaunce theyr Pikes, and ſo they march without anie firmneſſe, which is a verie ill thing. And to ſhunne it, it is better that the Corſlets ſhould enter by the harguebuzerie marching the pikes, and when they come to the end of the lane where the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſtandeth, without parting or opening, they ſhoulde vaunce them, ſtaying in theyr araie, and ſo from hand to hande make the ranks following, and that the harguebuziers, as ſoone as the ranke of Pikes being vaunced come néere them, ſhould cloſe to it, and fill vp the ſaid ranke, following this order till the end, ſo that the ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron may be framed: and as well the Harguebuzes as Corſlettes ought to be ſo vſed in doing this, that it bee not neceſſarie that the Officer put them in order: and if two Companies enter to watch at one time, as it often chanceth, then they ſhoulde ioyne together into one ſquadron, taking the harguebuzerie at each flanke, and the Corſlets without marring the raies ſhould enter in the midſt, noting by the waie that the Standarde remaine alwayes in the centre of the people. And I haue proued this maner of ioining two Companies (being in hearſes) into one ſquadron, and diuers times cauſed it to be done at the entering of the watch, and it hath béene verie well thought of, and approued by Captaines of greate pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and experience. And though there were no other reaſon for it then this, that they which followe Warres, in all places and at all times, when and where they be together with theyr weapons in theyr handes, ought to frame themſelues in a ſquadron, without which they cannot haue ſuch perfection and ſtrength as is requſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, yet is it a moſt ſufficient cauſe. And beſides this, the profite which enſueth, by reaſon that the ſouldiers by theſe meanes and continuall practiſe, become ready and well inſtructed in matters of ſo great importance, is excéeding great. The Companies that watch when others enter, may not departe from the watch hill or place of Armes, vntill ſuch time as they that enter to watch, haue framed theyr ſquadron. But hauing theyr weapons in their hands and ſtanding at the ſides of the Court-gard, they muſt ſtay til they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19616:30"/> are all entered, and then they may depart orderly eache one to his lodging. The Seargeant Maior ought to be verie carefull in the daie time to viſite the Court-gardes, and ſo dooing he ſhall force both the officers and ſouldiers to looke to their wards, which they ought not in anie caſe to leaue, ſaue onely when they go to dinner, and that by order, each one in his turne with his tabling mate, or <hi>Tamarda.</hi> And when ſome forcible neceſſitie is offered, no ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ought to depart from his warde without leaue from his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ſéeing that the ſouldiers are no leſſe bound from that day that they entered into this profeſſion of warfare, to bee obedient vnto the Captaines and Officers, doing nothing without theyr leaue: then thoſe Friers that are tied to many ſtrait orders, are to theyr Priors or Wardens. For when they be entered into the Bookes of his Maieſties paie at the firſt daie of their ſouldierſhip, to ſerue rather in this Companie then in that, betokeneth and ſignifieth no other thing but this onely, that they promiſe and ſweare ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inwardly in heart, to ſerue theyr King or Prince, obeying all and euerie thing that the Officers of their Companies ſhall or doe command them touching his Maieſties ſeruice. But I meane not that they ſhal not be bound to obey the Officers of other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies. For they owe due obeyſance vnto all Officers, as well to the Officers of other companies, as to the Officers of theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies in all things concerning the orders by them giuen and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, eſpecially when they are ranked in a ſquadron, or march in order, or ſtanding at the watch, briefly, in all things appertaining vnto theyr Princes ſeruice. Yet this ought to bee noted, that no ſouldier ought to bee puniſhed for his diſobedience, vnleſſe it bee in ſuch things as concerne their prince his ſeruice. As when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne or deſpiſe anie Officer in matters touching the order. For in other particular &amp; priuate matters, that touch not the ſeruice of the King, the Officers are no leſſe bound to be humble, mécke, and vſe good behauiour toward the ſouldiers. <hi>Seruatis, ſeruandis,</hi> then the ſouldiers are to be towards them, and thoſe Officers that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt theyr games and priuate conuerſation, for theyr owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie paſſe the limites of ciuilitie, often abuſing certaine ſouldy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers both in words many times and alſo in déedes, ſhould be ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed. For thence it procéedeth that the ſouldiers afterwards ſet naught by them in matters of order and gouernment, beeing
<pb facs="tcp:19616:31"/> prouoked and ſtirred vp againſt them by their hard vſage, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as neuertheleſſe all Officers ought contrarily to loue and vſe all ſouldiers that are vnder theyr protection and gouernment, as their owne naturall ſonnes. And aboue all other the Seargeant Maior ought ſo to do, ſéeing that it may verie truly be ſayd, that he is the generall Father of all the ſouldiers that ſerue in his Regiment. Now Sir, ſéeing that the people are lodged, and I (to confeſſe the truth) weary of this our long diſcourſe, I wil conclude with telling you that it doth not onely appertaine vnto the Seargeant Maior to be the generall maiſter of all good diſcipline in Warres, and to be the onely and vniuerſall procurer of all bodily and corporall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities for the ſouldiers, but he ought alſo to haue no leſſe regard and care of theyr ſoules: perſecuting and baniſhing all publique ſinne out of the Armie, as leude liuers, théeues, and all ſuch as liue diſſolutely and ſhamefully, and aboue all things he ought to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie watchfull and diligent, in not permitting anie one in the campe to blaſpheme the name of God, no not ſo much, if poſſible be, as to ſweare by his name, ſéeing that his diuine Maieſtie is ſo greatly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with both of thoſe horrible ſinnes. For in the Armie where there is no feare of God, and the foundation and principall intent be not to ſéeke his glorie and honour, there can nothing bee ſure, nothing good or certaine. Certes it is a griefe to beholde, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a people which ought to bee moſt zealous in the ſeruice of theyr Creator (ſéeing that the obtaining of the victorie doth not conſiſt in the vertue of the multitude of armes, nor in the force of wepons, but in the interceſſion of his grace, without whoſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence not ſo much as the leafe of a trée can be moued) are ſo many vices and abhominations. And verily we ſhould moſt iuſtly wéepe and deplore the weake remembraunce of men, when wee ſce that thoſe men are ſo forgetfull of Gods iuſt indgements, who aboue all other kindes of people haue death euerie moment more nigheſt and ſureſt before their eyes, and by all our ill kinde of liuing, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that when anie one taketh the Pike in hande to become a ſouldier, euen that daie he renounceth to bee a Chriſtian any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and maketh profeſſion euer after to be a Gentil, and (which is worſt of all) that our ignorance is ſo great, that many vnskilfull fellowes, and men without conſcience, thinke and holde opinion, that it is contrarie to a good and valiant ſouldier, to bee a good
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19616:31"/> Chriſtian and to feare God, but let all ſuch knowe, that contrarily it is impoſſible for anie man to be a right good and valyant ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, if he lacke the foundation of the feare of God, for though wee ſee many diſſolute and ill liuing ſouldiers verie reſolute to die, and being ſo determined fight couragiouſlie, daring both to buckle with theyr enemies, and to die, if occaſion be offered, yet wee may moſt truly turne this theyr boltnes to a beaſtly brutiſh minde, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it doth not procéede from true fortitude, which euer is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the feare of God, and it is rather a right temeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of bruite beaſts, and not of men indued with reaſon, for they conſider not, nor vnderſtand not how great a thing that is which they put in aduenture, and ſo for the moſt parte we ſée that ſuch men, vpon the leaſt occaſion in the world, though it bee moſt vyle and of no value, as ſome ſmal commoditie or vanitie: hazard their liues, which they ought to make ſo great account of, which they ought then to put in daunger with all theyr heartes, and making no account of it, when iuſtice and counſell requireth. God graunt it may pleaſe his mercie to take awaie the darkneſſe of this moſt cleere and apparant ignorance from our vnderſtanding, that wée may ſo knowe and ſerue him in this our temporall warfare, vnder the ſtandard and fayth of our ſoueraigne Lorde and inuincible Captaine Ieſus Chriſt, that we may deſerue by him to be made partaker of that celeſtiall and glorious warrefare in triumphant <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Maiſter <hi>Vargas.</hi> we haue made an end at one time both of our diſcourſe and our iourney alſo. And I beſéech you to pardon me if I haue not bin able to ſatiſfie your requeſt according to your deſire, for my ſimple talent is no farther extended: and be fully perſuaded that I haue not taken this paines ſo much for my pleaſure, as to accompliſh your deſire, which paines I ſhall thinke ill beſtowed if you take it in part of my ſeruice toward you: and now good Sir, let vs fall to ſuch meate as we haue here, for it may be your chamber-fellow hath alreadie dined.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>I am beholding vnto you for your curteſie, and you well knowe that it is not new or ſtrange to me to take part with you at dinner, but as for this daie I meane not any more to weary you, for if I went to dine with you, I am certaine that ſéeing you haue now ſo fully ſatiſfied me, in that I deſired ſo gréedilie to know
<pb facs="tcp:19616:32"/> concerning the Office of the Seargeant Maior, (which amongſt many other good turnes and déedes of true friendſhippe which I haue receiued of you I account not the leaſt) I ſhould not leaue to ſpeak of the other points which I mentioned yeſterdaie vnto you: but I am contented for this time, ſo you will ſome other daie (if occaſion bée offered) with ſome ſhorte diſcourſe daine to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie my deſire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Londonno.</speaker>
               <p>I will refuſe no paines to do you ſeruice, and ſo God be your guide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vargas.</speaker>
               <p>Hee bée with you alſo and all others.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19616:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
